大地惊雷
虽无人追赶  恶人亦仓皇逃跑
旧约: 箴言  第二十八章  第一节
背景音乐  依靠在上帝的臂膀下
"Leaning on the everlasting arms"
人们不会相信
People did not give it credence
一个小女孩能离开家乡
that a young girl could leave home.
在冰天雪地的寒冬为父亲报仇
And go off in the winter time to avenge her father's blood.
但事实就是如此
But it did happen.
那个懦夫汤姆・切尼射杀我父亲的时候
I was just fourteen years of age
我只有十四岁
when a coward by the name of Tom Chaney shot my father down.
他不但杀了我父亲  抢走他的马
And robbed him of his life, and his horse.
还拿走了他裤袋里的两块加州金块
And two California gold pieces that he carried in his trouser pant.
切尼是个雇工
Chaney was a hired man.
爸爸让他到史密斯堡
And Papa had taken him up to Fort Smith
帮忙带回他买下的小野马驹
to help lead back a string of mustang ponies he'd bought.
在城里  切尼被美酒吸引
In town, Chaney had followed to drink.
开始赌博  输光了身上所有的钱
And cards, and lost all his money.
他认为他被骗了
He got it into his head he was being cheated.
回到住处取他的那把亨利步枪
And went back to the boarding house for his Henry Rifle.
当父亲试图阻止他时
When Papa tried to intervene.
切尼开枪杀了他
Chaney shot him.
切尼逃跑了
Chaney fled.
他本可以牵着马慢慢走的
He could have walked his horse.
因为那座镇上的人没有一个去追赶他
For not a soul in that city could be bothered to give chase.
切尼自以为能逃过制裁
No doubt Chaney fancied himself, scott free.
但是他错了
But he was wrong.
这个世界任何东西都是有代价的
You must pay for everything in this world,
欠下的终究都会被偿还
one way or another.
除了上帝的恩泽
There is nothing free,
没有什么是免费的
except the grace of God.
是他吗
Is that the man?
是我父亲
That is my father.
如果你想亲吻他
If you would like to kiss him,
请便吧
It would be all right.
他回家了
He's gone to home.
感谢上帝
Praise the Lord.
为什么这么贵
Why is it so much?
棺木的选材
The quality of the casket.
还有防腐的材料
And of the embalming.
死者保持这样的外表是需要时间和工艺的
The life like appearance requires time and art.
化学药剂十分昂贵  帐单里有详细价格
And the chemicals come dear, the particulars are in your bill.
如果你想亲吻他  请便
If you'd like to kiss him, It would be all right.
谢谢您  他的灵魂已经消散了
Thank you, the spirit has flow.
你电报上说只要五十美元
Your wire said fifty dollars.
你没说清楚他是要被运输的
You did not specify that he was to be shipped.
我们只有六十美元
Well sixty dollars is every cent we have.
我们都没有钱住店了
That leaves nothing for our board.
亚内尔  你去看着遗体
Yarnell you can see to the body
运到火车站  然后护送回家
transport to the train station, and company it home.
我今晚会在这儿过夜
I'll have to sleep here tonight.
我还需要整理遗物和处理其他事宜
I still have to collect father's things and see some other business.
你母亲从没说过你要来办什么其他事宜
Your mama didn't say nothing about you settling no business here.
这是妈妈不知道的事
It's business mama dosen't know about.
好了  亚内尔  你可以走了
It's all right Yarnell, I dismiss you.
我可不这么认为
I am not sure.
转告我妈不要签署任何文件
Tell mama not to sign anything
一切等我回家后将父亲体面安葬好再说
until I return home and see that Papa is buried in his mason's apron.
你的出价可以接受  但我要在这过夜
Your terms are agreeable, if I might pass the night here.
在这儿  和这些死人一起吗
Here, among these people?
"这些死人"吗
These people?
待会儿还有三个心灵要在这里安息
I'm expecting three more souls.
苏里文  史密斯还有狗舌头
Sullivan, Smith, and His-tongue-in-the-rain.
女士们先生们  听好了
Ladies and gentlemen, beware
好好培养孩子  让他们走上正路
and train up your children the way that they should go!
你们看看现在的我
You see what has become of me.
因为喝酒
Because of drink.
我杀了一个人
I killed a man.
就因为争抢一把小折刀
In a triffiling quarrel over a pocket knife.
如果我年轻的时候能受到良好的教育
If I had received good instruction as a child...
请问哪位是警长
Could you point out the sheriff?
那个大胡子
Him with the moustaches.
今天我本可以和我妻子儿女在一起
I would be with my wife and children today.
我不知道他们以后会怎么样
I do not know what is to become of them.
但是我希望妻子不会放手不管孩子们
But I hope and pray that she will not slight them
让他们成为社会的败类
and compel them to go into low company.
好吧
Well.
我杀了一个不该杀的人
I killed the wrong man,
这就是我在这的原因
is the which why I'm here.
如果我没杀错的话
Had I killed the man I meant to.
我肯定不会被判死刑的
I don't believed I'd a been convicted.
我看到人群中  有些人还不如我呢
I see men out there in that crowd, that's worse than me.
好了
Okay.
我被绞死之前  我想说的是
Before I hang, I would like to say.
没有  我们没抓到他
Naw, we ain't arrested him.
他们没追上他  跑得太快了
Ain't caught up to him, but he lit out for the Territory.
我觉得他投靠幸运奈德・彼伯了
I would think that he throwed in with Lucky Ned Pepper,
他们昨天在波托河旁抢劫了一辆邮车
whose gang robbed a mail hack yesterday at the Poteau River.
那为什么您没有去搜捕他呢
Well, why are you not looking for him?
印第安区不在我的管辖范围内
I ain't no authority in the Indian Nation.
汤姆・切尼现在归美国法警管了
Tom Chaney is the business of the U.S. Marshal now.
那他们什么时候去抓他呢
When will they arrest him?
近期是不太可能了  法警的人手不够
Not soon, I'm afraid, the Marshals are not well staffed.
我实话跟你说吧
And I'll tell you, frankly,
切尼是通缉犯名单上的最后一个
Chaney is at the end of a long list of fugitives and malefactors.
我能雇个法警去追捕汤姆・切尼吗
Could I hire a Marshal to pursue Tom Chaney?
你是不是经常雇佣一些赏金猎人啊
You have a lot of experience with bounty hunters, do you?
怎么可能呢
That is a silly question.
我是来处理父亲后事的
I am here to settle my father's affairs.
-就你一个人吗  -只有我能做
- All alone. - I am the person for it.
我妈的数学很差
Mama was never any good at sums.
而且她大字不识两个
And she could hardly spell 'cat'.
我要看到杀害我父亲的人被处以绞刑
I intend to see Papa's killer hanged.
好吧
Well, nothing prevents you
你的确可以雇佣法警
from offering a reward or from so informing the Marshals.
但报酬要丰厚  这样才有人会去
It had to be real money though, to be persuasive.
切尼现在已经过河到了查克托区
Chaney's across the river, in Choctaw Nation.
查克托区: 印第安人半自治区
我会处理钱的问题  谁是最好的法警
I will see to the money. Who's the best Marshal?
我得想想
I'd have to weigh that.
威廉姆・沃特斯追捕能力过人
William Waters, is the best tracker.
他有一半卡曼其血统
He is half Comanche,
卡曼其族(北美印第安之一族)
看他追捕赏心悦目
and it is something to see him cut for the sign.
最暴脾气的要属大公鸡考伯恩
The meanest, is Rooster Cogburn.
他铁面无私  真正的硬汉
He is a pitiless man. Double tough.
他无所畏惧
Fear don't enter into his thinking.
但是他嗜酒如命
Hmm, he loves to pull a cork.
最好的人选应该是奎因
The best is probably, L.T. Quinn.
他总能活捉罪犯
He brings his prisoners in alive.
也许会因此偶尔失手
Now he may let one slip by now and again,
但是  他相信
but he believes that
就算是罪大恶极的人  也应秉公处理
even the worst of men, is entitled to a fair shake.
我在哪儿能找到这个大公鸡
Where can I find this, Rooster?
厕所有人了
The jakes is occupied.
我知道考伯恩先生
I know it is occupied Mr. Cogburn.
我有事找您
As I said, I have business with you.
我的事情更紧急
I have prior business.
您已经在这里待了很久了  考伯恩先生
You've been at it for quite some time, Mr. Cogburn.
我的事情想做多久就多久
There is no clock for my business!
去死吧  你怎么找到我的
The hell with you! How did you spot me here?
警长叫我去酒吧找找
The sheriff told me to look in the saloon.
酒吧的人说你在这儿  我们得谈谈
In the saloon they referred me here. We must talk.
酒吧根本就不接待女人
Women ain't allowed in the saloon.
我不算顾客  我才十四岁
I was not there as a customer. I am fourteen years old.
厕所有人了
The jakes is occupied.
有段时间不会出来
Will be for some time.
罗斯  运往耶尔县  在车站存放
晚上好
Good evening.
如果你想睡在棺材里  请便吧
If you would like to sleep in a coffin, It would be all right.
棉花你多少钱收
How much are you paying for cotton?
九分五收中低档次的  十分收优质的
Nine and a half, for low and middlin' and ten for ordinary.
我门很早就把货出手了
We got most of ours out early.
我卖给了小岩城的维兹绅兄弟
I sold to the Wizten brothers in Little Rock
价格是十一分
for eleven cents.
那你应该把剩下的也卖给他们啊
Then I suggest you take the balance of it to the Witzen brothers.
我们的确吧剩下的卖了
We take the balance to Witzen.
十分五的价格
We got ten and a half.
你为什么要来告诉我这些呢
Why'd you come here to tell me this?
我们本来打算明年来这里做生意的
I thought we might shop around up here next year.
这么看来  我们在小岩城那边就好了
But I guess we are doing alright in Little Rock.
我是麦蒂・罗斯
I'm Mattie Ross.
弗兰克・罗斯是我父亲
Daughter of Frank Ross.
真是可怜啊
Aw, tragic thing.
我想说  你的父亲令我印象深刻
May I say, your father impressed me.
他的人品很好
With his manly qualities.
他做商人分文必争  却还是个绅士
He was a close trader, but he acted a gentleman.
我的提议是将我父亲买下的小马驹
My propose was to sell those ponies back to you,
再卖还给你
that my father brought.
我想这恐怕是不行
Well that I fear, is out of the question.
我保证会给你送到的
I will see that they are shipped to you,
而且会尽快
at my earliest convenience.
我们现在不想要也不需要小马驹了
We don't want the ponies now, we don't need them.
我想这与我无关吧
Well that hardly concerns me.
你父亲买下它们  并且付钱了
Your father brought the ponies, and paid for them.
我们两清了  我有收据的
And there is an end to it. I have the bill of sale.
那我要三百块的补助
And I want 300 dollars
因为我父亲的马是在你的马棚失窃的
for Papa's saddle horse that was stolen from your stable.
你应该找偷马的人去讨账
You'll have to take that up with the man who stole the horse.
汤姆・切尼偷走了
Tom Chaney stole the horse
你应该负责保管好的马
while it was in your care.
你要对此负责
You were responsible.
我很钦佩你的不懈努力
Yeah, I admire your sand.
但是你应该知道  我对此是不负责任的
But I believe you'll find I'm not liable for such claims.
你是保管人
You were the custodian.
如果你是开银行的而银行被抢劫了
If you were a bank and were robbed.
你不能就告诉储户们顺其自然吧
You could not simply tell your depositors to go hang.
别跟我打比方
I do not entertain hypotheticals.
世道本来就已经很烦人了
The world as it is is vexing enough.
其次  你对马的估价过高了
Secondly your evaluation of the horse is high.
你至少高估了两百块  你多大了
By about two hundred dollars. How old are you?
我跟你说  我的估价绝对是低价
If anything, my prices is low.
茱迪是一匹优质的赛马种马
My Judy was a fine racing mare.
我看到她
I've seen her
能驮着一个很重的骑手跳过八栅栅栏
jump a eight-rail fence with a heavy rider.
-我十四岁 -是吗  真有意思
- I am fourteen. - Oh, well, it's all very interesting.
小马驹是你们的了  你得收下
The ponies are yours, take them.
你父亲的马是被杀人犯偷走的
Your father horse was stolen by a murderous criminal.
鉴于我们之间的默示协议
I have provided reasonable protection
我已经为它做了足够的保护措施
for the creature as per our implicit agreement.
我的马厩管理员牙齿都被打掉了
My watchmen had his teeth knocked out,
他现在只能喝汤了
and can take only soup.
那我们法庭上见吧
That would take it to law.
你没有理由起诉我
You have no case.
阿肯色州洁特律师也许不会同意
Lawyer J. Noble Daggett of Dardanelle, Arkansas may think otherwise.
陪审团估计也不会同意你的观点
As might a jury.
一个寡妇和三个孩子的诉状胜算不会小
Petitioned by a widow and three small children.
我会往你父亲的账户里
I will pay two hundred dollars
打两百美元
to your fathers estate.
前提条件是  我要收到你律师的文件
When I have in my hand a letter from your lawyer,
免除我到今天为止的一切责任
absolving me of all liability from the beginning of the world to date.
茱迪的价格是两百块
I'll take two hundred dollars for Judy,
小马驹是一百块
plus one hundred for the ponies.
另有二十五块
And twenty five dollars
是那匹汤姆・切尼留下的灰马
for the grey horse that Tom Chaney left.
市场上很容易就能四十块出手的
He was easily worth forty.
那一共是三百二十五块
That is three hundred and twenty-five dollars total.
小马驹不算在内  我是不会买的
The ponies have no part in it. I will not buy them.
那茱迪的价格就是三百二十五块
Then the price for Judy is three hundred and twenty-five dollars.
就算是飞马我也不会出这么多钱的
I would not pay three hundred and twenty-five dollars for winged Pegasus.
还有  那匹灰马根本就不是你的
As for the grey horse, it does not belong to you.
那匹马是我父亲借给汤姆・切尼的
The grey horse was lent to Tom Chaney by my father.
切尼只是借用而已
Chaney only had the use of him.
我会付给你二百二十五块
I would pay two hundred and twenty five dollars.
但我要留着那匹灰马
And keep the grey horse.
另外还有小马驹我也收下
And I want the ponies.
我不接受
I cannot accept that.
我离开这里之后就不会有和解了
There will be no settlement after I leave this office
-我们法庭上见  -好吧  我让步
- and it will go to law. - All right, this is my last offer.
两百五十块
Two hundred and fifty dollars.
前提是我拿到先前说的免责文件
For that I get the release, previously discussed.
还有你父亲的马鞍
And I keep your father's saddle.
灰马不由得你来卖
The grey horse is not yours to sell.
那马鞍是无价的  我要留着它
The saddle is not for sale. I will keep it.
洁特律师会证明那匹灰马的归属权
Lawyer Dagget will prove ownership of the grey horse.
他会发函向你追缴非法强占财产的
He will come after you with a writ of replevin.
什么  好吧  听好了
What? All right, now look, listen very carefully.
我不会再让步了
As I will not bargain further.
我要回小马驹
I'll will take the ponies back,
那匹灰马本来就是我的
and the grey horse, which is mine.
妥协价是...
And settle...
三百美元  就这么说定了
For three hundred dollars. Now you must take that or leave it.
我豁出去了
And I do not much care which it is.
杰特律师是不会让我
Lawyer Daggett would not wish me to
接受任何低于三百二十五块的补偿的
consider anything under three hundred and twenty-five dollars.
但是我想三百二十块就够了
But I will settle for three hundred and twenty.
如果那二十块是提前支付的话
If I am given twenty in advance.
好了  现在我们再说说那个马鞍
Now here's what I have to say about that saddle.
弗兰克・罗斯的女儿吗
Frank Ross's daughter.
哦  可怜的孩子
Oh, poor child.
你是准备在这儿呆一阵子
Are you are gonna staying with us,
还是你马上就回家看你妈妈呢
or you hurrying back home to your Mama?
我想留在这儿  如果方便的话
I'll stay here, if you can have me.
我昨晚在收敛师那儿过的夜
I just spend last night at the undertakers.
陪着三具尸体
In the company of three corpses.
我觉得我像是以西结
I felt like Ezekiel.
以西结: 希伯来先知
旧约圣经以西结书之作者
在死亡谷中
In valley of the dry bones.
上帝保佑你
Then, God bless you.
你和祖母特纳睡在一个房间
Now that you'll be rooming with, Grandma Turner.
我们得挤一挤了
We had to double up,
因为许多人都前来看绞刑
what with all the people in town come to see the hanging.
这些是你父亲屋中的遗物
This was in your poor father's room.
这就是所有的东西了
That is everything.
这栋房子里没有小偷的
There are no light fingers in this house.
如果你需要什么来装那把枪
If you need something for to tote the gun around?
我可以给你一个面粉袋  只要五分钱
I can give you an empty flour sack for a nickel.
他在那儿发现了什么
...about what he found up here,
我们离波特警官很近
and we're close enough to deputy Marshal Potter
所以我们就靠近那里去调查了
that we thought we'd better ride over ourselves and investigate.
那么你看到什么了
And what did you see when you arrived?
一个女人  在院子那里
A woman, was out in the yard.
她死了  脸上都是苍蝇
Dead with blow flies on her face.
一个老人在院子里面
The old man was inside
他的胸脯被霰弹枪打开花了
with his breast opened by a scatter-gun
他的脚被烧焦了
and his feet burned.
他那时候还活着  但也只剩一口气了
He was still alive, but just was.
他说是沃顿兄弟俩干的
Said it was them two Wharton boys had done it.
-他们聚在一起  喝醉了  -反对
- Rode up, drunk. - Objection.
道听途说
Hearsay.
那可是临终遗言  法官大人
Dying declaration, your honor.
反对无效  请继续  考伯恩先生
Objection's overruled. Proceed Mr. Cogburn.
然后兄弟二人  奥多斯和赛思将他推倒在地
Them two Wharton boys, Odus and C.C. throwed down on him,
问他钱在哪儿  但是他没说
and asked him where his money was, but he wouldn't tell them.
他们在他脚上抹上松子油  点火拷问他
They lit pine nut held them to his feet.
他说钱在一个水果罐头中
He told them the money was in the fruit jar.
在烟熏屋旁的一块灰色岩石下面
Under a grey rock at the corner of the smoke house.
然后呢
And then?
他死了  死时相当痛苦
Well he died on us, Passed away in considerable pain.
然后你做了什么
What'd you do then?
我和波特警官找到烟熏屋
I made Marshal Potter and went out to the smoke house
发现那块岩石被搬走了
and that rock had been moved,
然后那罐钱也不见了
the jar with the money in it was gone.
-反对  纯属猜测  -反对有效
-Objection, speculative. -Sustained.
你们在烟熏屋旁边找到了那个灰岩石
You found a flat grey rock, in the corner of the smoke house.
下面有个洞
With a hollowed out space beneth it.
如果被告要陈述证据
If the prosecutor is going to give evidence,
我希望他能宣誓
I suggest he be sworn.
考伯恩先生  你在烟熏屋附近
Mr. Cogburn. What did you find,
找到了什么东西
if anything, in the corner of that smokehouse?
有一块平整的灰色岩石
We found a flat gray rock with
下面有个洞  里面什么都没有
a hollowed-out space under it. Nothing there.
-然后呢  -没有罐子  什么也没有
- Well then what did you...? - No jar or nothing.
那之后你做什么了吗
Well, what did you do then?
然后  我去到沃顿兄弟那里
Well, rode up to the Wharton boys there,
离北福克河与加拿大河的汇流处不远
near where the North Fork strikes the Canadian.
-..加拿大河支流  -你发现了什么
- ...branch of the Canadian. - What did you find?
我用望远镜看到兄弟俩和他们的父亲艾伦
I had my glass and we spotted the two boys and their old daddy Aaron.
他们和一些畜养猪在溪流岸边
down on the creek bank with some hogs.
他们杀了一头小猪
They'd killed a shoat.
然后便生火烧水
And a fire built up under a wash pot for scalding water.
之后你做了什么
What did you do?
我对着艾伦喊  我们是美国法警
Announced we was U.S. Marshals, I hollered out to Aaron.
我要和他儿子们谈谈
I needed to talk to his two boys.
他抡起斧子
He raised an axe,
开始咒骂我们  并且侮辱法庭公正
and commence to cussing us and blackguarding this court.
那之后呢
What did he do then?
我后退几步  躲开斧子
I backed away from the axe.
试着和他讲点道理
Tried to talked some sense into him.
就在这个时候
While this was going on,
赛思躲在升起的蒸汽后面
C.C. edges over to the wash pot there, behind the steam.
拿起一把双管猎枪
And picks up a shot gun.
波特看到了  但是一切都太迟了
Potter seen him, but it was too late.
赛思对着波特开火了
C.C. Wharton pulled out on Potter with one barrel.
然后想要打我  我就开枪了
Turned to do the same for me and I shot him.
他父亲也抡起了斧子
And the old man raised the axe.
我开枪打了他
And I shot him.
奥多斯想要逃跑  我也对他开了一枪
Odus lit out, and I shot him.
赛思和他老爸倒地后就断气了
C.C. Wharton and Aaron Wharton were dead when they hit the ground,
而奥多斯只是被击伤了
Odus was just winged.
那你发现装着一百二十美元的罐子了吗
Did you find the jar with a hundred and twenty dollars in it?
-反对  暗示性问题  -反对有效
- Leading. - Sustained.
之后发生了什么
What happened then?
的确找到了里面有一百二十块钱的罐子
Found a jar with a hundred and twenty dollars in it.
奥多斯后来怎样了
What became of Odus Wharton?
他在那儿坐着呢
There he sits.
您可以提问了  高迪先生
You may ask, Mr. Goudy.
谢谢  巴罗先生
Thank you Mr. Barlow.
考伯恩先生
Mr. Cogburn.
在你担任美国法警职务的四年中
In your four years as a U.S. Marshal.
你对多少人开了枪
How many men have you shot?
我从不无缘无故开枪打人
Never shot nobody that didn't ask for it.
你并没有回答我的问题
Well that was not the question.
多少个
How many?
开枪打的还是射杀的
Shot or killed?
咱们就限定在你射杀的吧
Let us restrict it to killed
这样数目不至于大得说不清
So that we may have a manageable figure.
大概十二个
About twelve.
或者十五个  制止斗殴  自卫反击之类的
Fifteen. Stopping men in flight, defending myself, et cetera.
他说大概十二个
Around twelve he says.
或者十五个
Or fifteen.
那么多  你甚至都没法给出准确的数字
So many, you cannot keep a precise count.
我检查了案件卷宗  可以提供准确的数目
I have examined the records, and can supply the accurate figure.
我估计算上沃顿家的那两人  得有二十三个
I believe them two Wharton boys makes it twenty three.
就单单这一家
And how many members of this one family,
沃顿家  你杀了多少个人
the Wharton family, have you killed?
直系的  还是...
Immediate, or...
你是否还开枪打死了家中的兄弟达布・沃顿
Did you also shoot Dub Wharton, brother?
以及异母兄弟克里特・沃顿
And Clete Wharton, half-brother?
噢  克里特卖烈酒给切诺基人
Oh, Clete was selling ardent spirits to the Cherokee.
他拿着个大螺栓向我冲来
He come at me with a king bolt.
大螺栓
A king bolt?
你带着枪  他朝你冲过去
You are armed, and he advanced upon you.
手里就拿着个大螺栓
With nothing more than a King bolt?
还是从马车牵引架上卸下来的
From a wagon tongue?
我见过有人被比螺栓还小的东西
I've seen men badly tore up with
撕成重伤  我是在正当防卫
nothing bigger than a king bolt. I defended myself.
回到我们的案子
Returning to the other encounter.
你碰上了艾伦还有他剩下的两个儿子
With Aaron Wharton, and his two remaining sons.
你从藏身之处猛然跃起
You sprang from cover.
手里拿着左轮枪
With revolver in hand.
-就是那样  -上好子弹准备射击
-That'd be it. -Loaded and cocked.
要是没上好子弹  我还怎么开枪
Well if it ain't loaded and cocked, it don't shoot.
和他的儿子一样
And like his son,
艾伦冲向了一个带着武器的人
Aaron Wharton advanced against an armed man.
可他也有武器  他举着把斧头
Well he was armed, he had an axed raised.
我记得你曾作证说你后退躲开了艾伦
I believe you testified you backed away from Aaron Wharton.
-没错  -朝哪个方向后退
-That's right. -Which direction were you going?
我后退的时候都是向后的
I always go backwards, when I'm backing up.
很有趣
Very amusing.
他朝你冲去的方式和克里特差不多
Now, he advanced upon you much in the manner of Clete Wharton
拿着个可怜的螺栓
menacing you with that little
或者一卷报纸之类的玩意儿来威胁你
king bolt or rolledup newspaper or whatever it was.
对  他开始咒骂
Yes sir. He commenced to cussing
-嘴里放着狠话  -然后你向后退
-and laying about with threats. -And you were backing away.
枪战发生之前你后退了多少步
How many steps before the shooting started?
七八步吧
Uh, seven, eight steps.
很好  而沃顿先生穷追不舍
Good, and Wharton keeping pace.
离他的营火越来越远
Advancing away from his campfire.
七  八  步
Seven, eight, steps.
那有多远
What would that be?
十五  或者二十英尺
Fifteen, twenty feet?
差不多吧
I suppose.
你能否向陪审团解释一下  考伯恩先生
Will you explain to this jury, Mr. Cogburn.
为什么沃顿先生被发现的时候
Why Mr. Wharton was found
倒在他的手盆边上  一只手还在火里
immediately by his wash pot, one arm in the fire.
-袖子和手都烧着了  -呃
- His sleeve and hand smoldering. - Well...
你是否在射杀他之后还搬动了尸体
Did you move the body after you shot him?
我为什么要那么干
Why would I do that?
你否认把尸体拖到营火旁边并把手扔进去
You did not drag the body over to the fire? Fling his arm in?
-我否认  先生  -两个证人
-No, sir. -Two witnesses.
两个目击了事发现场的证人
Who arrived on the scene
能够为尸体的位置作证
will testify to the location of the body.
你不记得搬动过尸体
You do not remember moving the body.
那么  这就是一起当可怜的沃顿先生正在
So it was, a cold blooded bushwhack,
照料营火的时候发生的冷血袭击
while poor Mr. Wharton was tending his campfire.
抗议
Objection.
要是尸体真在那儿  可能是我搬的
I, if that was where the body was I might have moved him.
我记不清了
I do not remember.
为什么你要去搬动尸体  考伯恩先生
Why, would you move the body, Mr. Cogburn?
那些猪崽在附近跑来跑去  可能是它们挪的
Them hogs rooting around they might have moved him.
我记不清了
I do not remember.
傻逼娘娘腔
Pencil-neck son of a bitch.
-考伯恩先生  -干嘛
-Mr. Cogburn. -What do you want?
我想跟您谈一会儿
I'd like to talk to you a minute.
干嘛
What is it?
他们告诉我您是真正有勇气和毅力的人
They tell me you're a man with, true grit.
你想干嘛  小女孩
What do you want, girl?
有话直说  该吃晚饭了
Speak up, it is suppertime.
我来卷吧
Let me do that.
你的烟丝太干了
Your makings are too dry.
我在找在蒙纳克客栈门口
I am looking for the man who shot and killed my father,
枪杀了我父亲弗兰克・罗斯的男人
Frank Ross, in front of the Monarch boarding house.
他的名字叫汤姆・切尼
The man's name is Tom Chaney.
他们说他逃到了印第安人的地盘
They say he's over in Indian Territory,
我需要有人帮我追捕他
and I need somebody to go after him.
你叫什么  小女孩
What's your name, girl.
我叫麦蒂・罗斯
My name is Mattie Ross.
我们家住在耶尔县
We're located in Yell County.
我妈妈在家里照顾
My mother is at home looking after
我的妹妹维多利亚和弟弟小弗兰克
my sister Victoria and my brother little Frank.
你最好回家去
You best go home to them.
他们需要人照顾
They'll need help with the charges.
切尼身上背着逃犯逮捕令
There is a fugitive warrant out for Chaney.
只要你能逮捕他  政府会奖励你两美元
The government will pay you two dollars
每追踪一英里额外奖励十美分
for bringing him in plus ten cents a mile for each of you.
在这基础上  我会付给你五十美元的酬劳
On top of that, I will pay you a fifty dollar reward.
你到底是谁
What are you?
你那兜里装着什么
What you got there in your poke?
天啊  一把柯尔特龙骑兵左轮
By God! A Colt Dragoon!
你个小不点
You're no bigger than a corn nubbin,
拿着这么一把枪要干嘛
what're you doing with a pistol like that?
我打算用它杀掉汤姆・切尼
Well I intend to kill Tom Chaney with it.
杀掉汤姆・切尼
Kill Tom Chaney?
要是法律没能惩罚他的话
Well if the law fails to do so.
那这枪能帮上你的忙
Well that piece will do the job for you.
不过你最好找好支点
If you can find a high stump
身后顶着墙[形容这枪后坐力大]
to rest it on and a wall to put behind you.
这里没有人认识我父亲
Nobody here knew my father and I'm,
而且除非我亲自动手
afraid nothing's is going to be done about Chaney
恐怕切尼会逍遥法外
except I do it.
我弟弟还是个孩子
My brother is a child,
我母亲优柔寡断  又悲痛致残
and my mother is indecisive and hobbled by grief.
我不相信你有五十美元
I don't believe you have fifty dollars.
我跟斯通希尔上校签了合约
I have a contract with Colonel Stonehill
他明天或者后天就会支付给我
which he will make payment on tomorrow or the next day
一旦律师签好了手续
once a lawyer countersigns.
我不相信关于金钱的任何事情
I don't believe in fairy tales or sermons or stories about money,
小妹妹  不过谢谢你帮我卷的烟
baby sister. But thank you for the cigarette.
你妈妈还在等你回家吧  宝贝
Isn't your Mama expecting you home, dear?
我的事还没处理完
My business is not yet finished.
弗洛依夫人  有新空出来房间吗
Mrs. Floyd, have any rooms opened up?
特纳奶奶那间  那床太挤了
Grandma Turner... the bed is quite narrow.
后面二楼倒是空出来了
The second-floor back did open up
但是  门廊上的那位先生
But uh, that gentleman on the porch,
刚住进去
has just taken it.
不过别担心  宝贝
Oh but don't worry yourself, dear.
你没有打扰到特纳奶奶
You're not disturbing Grandma Turner.
我叫勒波义夫
My name is LeBoeuf.
我刚从耶尔县过来
I just come from Yell County.
我们耶尔县可没有你这么滑稽的牛仔
We have no rodeo clowns in Yell County.
你这些俏皮话对我是没用的
A saucy line will not get you far with me.
我昨天早上见了你母亲
I saw your mother yesterday morning.
她让你马上回家
She said for you to come right on home.
你到那儿去干嘛
What was your business there?
我想你认识这个男人
This is a man I think you know.
你管他叫汤姆・切尼
You called him Tom Chaney.
至少我想是这样  在我追踪他的
I believe. All the months I've been
这几个月间  他是瑟伦・切尔姆斯福特
tracking him he has used the name, Theron Chelmsford.
也是约翰・托德・安德森
John Todd Andersen,
还用过别的假名
and others.
他在路易斯安那州的门罗
He dallied in Monroe, Louisiana,
和阿肯色州的派恩布拉夫等地游荡
and Pine Bluff, Arkansas
然后他出现在你父亲那儿
Before turning up at your fathers place.
那为什么你没在阿肯色州的派恩布拉夫
Then why did you not catch him at,
或者路易斯安那州的门罗抓住他
Pine Bluff, Arkansas or Monroe, Louisiana?
他特别狡诈
He is a crafty one.
我还以为他是那种粗人呢
I thought him slow-witted myself.
他只是看上去那样而已
That was his act.
不错的伪装
It was a good one.
你是执法者吗
Are you some kind of law?
没错
That's right
我是德州骑警
I'm a Texas Ranger.
在那个州  你大概还算是个人物
That may make you a big noise in that state
在阿肯色州你该知道德州式的
in Arkansas you should mind that your Texas trappings and title
马具和头衔可没什么吸引力
do not make you an object of fun.
你为什么一直徒劳地在追捕切尼
Why have you been ineffectually pursuing Chaney?
他在德州韦科枪杀了州参议员比波斯
He shot and killed a state senator named Bibbs in Waco, Texas.
比波斯家发出了悬赏
Bibbs family have put out a reward.
切尼为什么会枪杀州参议员
How came Chaney to shoot a state senator?
我听说与一条狗的纠纷有关
My understanding is there was an argument about a dog.
你知道切尼现在何处吗
You know anything about the whereabouts of Chaney?
他在印第安人的地盘
He is in the Territory, and I
而且我对你拿到赏金不抱多大希望
hold out little hope for you earning your bounty.
-怎么说  -我的人会先你一步拿到赏金
-Why is that? -My man will beat you to it.
我雇了一位最厉害的执行法警
I have hired a deputy marshal, the toughest one they have
而且他对据说和切尼联系密切的
and he is familiar with the Lucky Ned Pepper gang
奈德・彼伯帮很熟悉
that they say Chaney has tied up with.
那我就加入你和你的法警吧
Well, I will throw in with you and your Marshal.
不  考伯恩警官和我两个人就够了
No, Marshal Cogburn and I are fine.
我们合作会更有优势
It'll be to our mutual advantage.
我想你那位警官会对那地方很熟悉
Your Marshal, I presume, knows the Territory.
而我熟悉切尼  活捉他至少得两个人
I know Chaney. It is at least a two-man job taking him alive.
抓到切尼之后他得被押回史密斯堡受绞刑
When Chaney is taken he is coming back to Fort Smith to hang.
我不能让他因为
I am not having him go
枪杀了什么州议员而被押回德州受绞刑
to Texas to hang for shooting some senator.
他在哪儿受绞刑并不重要  对不对
It is not important where he hangs, it is?
对我来说重要
It is to me.
对你来说呢
Is it to you?
对我来说这意味着一大笔钱
It means a great deal of money to me.
我跟了他好几个月
It's been many months' Work.
我很遗憾你的工资并不是按月支付
I'm sorry that you are paid piecework not on wages
还被这白痴耍得浪费了一整个冬天
and that you have been eluded the winter long by a halfwit.
你说的话可真是冷酷无情
You give out very little sugar with your pronouncements.
我坐在那儿看着你的时候
While I sat there watching
我还在考虑要不要夺取你的初吻
you I gave some thought to stealing a kiss
尽管你还小  又病泱泱的
though you are very young and sick and
而且  对我也没什么吸引力
unattractive to boot, but
可现在  我倒是想要
now I have a mind to give
用皮带好好抽你个五六下
you five or six good licks with my belt.
两样都不合我口味
One would be as unpleasant as the other.
我倒是给你个建议吧  把梳子沾湿
If you wet your comb,
说不定能把那头乱毛梳平
it might tame that cowlick.
麦蒂  我希望你能把这些事务
Mattie, I wish you would leave these matters
完全移交给我处理  或者至少得
entirely to me or at the very least
在签那些条约之前
give me the courtesy of
赏脸咨询在下的意见
consulting me before entering such agreements.
我不是在责怪你  可我不得不说你这种
I am not scolding you, but I am saying your head strong ways,
固执的作风总有一天将使你走进死胡同
will lead you into a tight corner one day.
我相信随信附上的文件
I trust the enclosed document
能让你处理完事务  回到耶尔县来
will let you conclude your business and return to Yell County.
您的  J・诺贝尔・达吉特
Yours, J. Noble Dagget.
你今天看起来就跟我昨天一样糟
I was as bad yesterday as you look today.
我被逼地跟特纳奶奶同床共枕
I was forced to share a bed with Grandma Turner.
我和特纳奶奶不熟
I'm not acquainted with Grandma Turner.
既然她住在这个城市
If she is a resident of this city
要是她染上了什么疾病  我可不奇怪
it does not surprise me that she carries disease.
这个疟疾肆虐的地方毁掉了我的身体
This malarial place has ruined my health.
也毁掉了我的生意
As it has my finances.
我欠你钱
I owe you money.
你可别认为我占了你便宜
You have not traded poorly.
噢  可不嘛
Oh, certainly not.
我为了一匹不属于我的马
I'm paying you for a horse
付给你一笔钱
I do not possess.
然后我还从你手上买回了一群没用的小马驹
And have bought back a string of useless ponies
我还卖不出去
Which I cannot sell again.
你忘了那匹灰马
You're forgetting the Grey horse.
-劣马  -你看问题的角度有失偏颇
-Crowbait. -You are looking at the thing in the wrong light.
我看问题的角度来自上帝永恒的真理
I am looking at it in the light of God's eternal truth.
你的病让你过于悲观了
Your illness is putting you down in the dumps.
你很快就会找到买家买那些小马了
You will soon find another buyer for the ponies.
我倒是有个暂定的订单  十美元一匹
Well I have a tentative offer of ten dollars per head.
来自小石城的菲茨肥皂厂
From the Pfitzer Soap Works of Little Rock.
就这么毁掉那些生气勃勃的小马太可惜了
It would be a shame to destroy such spirited horseflesh.
可惜就可惜吧  这生意本来就谈不成
So it would. I'm confident the deal will fall through.
我要匹小马
Look here, I need a pony
我会给你十美元来买一匹
and I will pay ten dollars for one of them.
不  那是批发价  不  不
No. That was lot price. No no.
等等
Wait a minute.
我们又做上生意了吗
Are we trading again?
这匹马真美
This one is beautiful.
他意识不到他身上有个骑手
He don't know he got a rider.
您太轻了
You're to light.
他以为身上有只虱子
He think he got a horsefly on him.
他精力非常旺盛
He's very spirited.
我就叫他"小黑"吧
I'll call him 'Little Blackie'.
好名字
Das a good name.
他爱吃什么
What does he like for a treat?
小姐  他是匹马
Well ma'am, he's a horse.
所以他爱吃苹果
So he likes apples.
替我谢谢斯通希尔先生
Thank Mr. Stonehill for me.
不  小姐  我没资格提您的名字
No ma'am, I ain't supposed to utter your name.
看  睡着了
See. Sleep.
没关系  我会叫醒他的
That is fine, I will wake him.
考伯恩警官
Marshal Cogburn.
是我  麦蒂・罗斯  你的雇主
It is I, Mattie Ross, your employer.
你还有多久能出发
How long til you are ready to go?
去哪儿
Go where?
去印第安区抓汤姆・切尼
Into the Indian Territory. In pursuit of Tom Chaney.
噢  你就是那个坐拥金山的可怜小女孩
Oh, You're the bereaved girl with stories of El Dorado.
哈  你有多少钱
Huh, how much money you got there?
我说抓到切尼就给你五十美元
I said fifty dollars to retrieve Chaney.
你不相信我
You did not believe me?
我不知道
Well, I did not know.
你让人捉摸不透
You are a hard one to figure.
你准备好出发要多长时间
How long for you to make ready to depart?
悠着点儿  小妹妹
Well uh, hold on sis.
我记得你的任务  我可不记得答应过
I remember your offer but do not remember agreeing to it.
要是我得去和奈德・彼伯帮干架
If I'm to go up against, Ned Pepper.
我得要一百美元
Then I'll need a hundred dollars.
就是这个价  一百美元
That much I can tell you. A hundred dollars.
逮回你的人  一百美元
To retrieve your man, a hundred dollars.
得先付五十美元
I will take that fifty dollars in advance.
当作路费花销
There will be expenses.
你这是在试图愚弄我
You are trying to take advantage of me.
我给你的是儿童折扣价
I am giving you the children's rate.
我可不是骗子  我只是个住在
I am not a sharper, I am an old man
中国人开的杂货铺后头睡在绳床上的老头
sleeping in a rope bed in a room behind a Chinese grocery.
我一无所有
I have nothing
你就想在威士忌里醉死吧
You want to be kept in whiskey.
我可用不着买那个
I don't have to buy that,
我没收就行
I confiscate it.
我可是法庭警官
I am an officer of the court.
谢谢
Ah, thank you.
一百美元  就这个价
Hundred dollars, that's the rate.
那我就不讨价还价了
I shall not niggle.
我们今天下午能出发吗
Can we depart this afternoon?
我们
We?
你不能去  这不包括在任务里
You're not going, that is no part of it.
你要是以为我会傻到给你五十美元然后
You have misjudge me if you think I am silly
眼巴巴看着你扬长而去  你就大错特错了
enough to give you fifty dollars and simply watch you ride off.
我是个合法的美国法警
I am a bonded U.S. Marshal.
那种话对我可没用
That weighs but little with me.
我得看着你把这事做完
I will see the thing done.
该死  我可不能一边扮硬汉
Damn ducks. I can't go after Ned Pepper
追捕奈德・彼伯  一边又照顾个小孩
and a band of hard men and look after a baby at the same time.
我可不是小孩
I am not a baby.
我可不会在那种房间里有张暖床
I will not be stopping at boarding
桌子上摆着热饭热菜的客栈里歇脚
houses where there is warm beds and hot grub on the table.
我会风驰电掣  风餐露宿
I'll be traveling fast and eating light.
最多在地上打个小盹儿
What little sleeping is done will take place on the ground.
我以前也露过一次营
Well I have slept out a night before.
爸爸去年夏天带我和小弗兰克
Papa took me and Little Frank
去佩蒂吉恩州立公园猎过一次浣熊
coon hunting last summer on the Petit Jean.
我们在森林里待了整整一晚上
We were in the woods all night.
我们升起了一大簇篝火  还讲鬼故事
We sat around a big fire and Yarnell told ghost stories.
我们玩的很开心
We had a good time.
猎浣熊
Coon hunting!?
咱这可不是什么猎浣熊
This ain't no coon hunt!
这主意和猎浣熊差不多
It is the same idea as a coon hunt.
这跟猎浣熊可差了十万八千里
It don't come within forty miles of being a coon hunt!
你不过是好大喜功而已
You are just trying to make your work sound harder than it is.
给你钱
Here is the money.
我的目标是抓住汤姆・切尼
Now I aim to get Tom Chaney,
要是你没胆  我就找个有胆子的人
and if you are not game, I will find somebody who is game.
到目前为止我发现你只会说空话
All I have heard out of you so far is talk.
我知道你能喝威士忌  还能打呼噜吐痰
I know you can drink whiskey and snore
躺在污秽的床上  抱怨自己悲惨的际遇
and spit and wallow in filth and bemoan your station.
然后就是自吹自擂
The rest has been braggadocio.
他们说你有勇气  所以我才来找你
They told me you had grit and that is why I came to you.
我花钱可不是雇你来说空话的
I am not paying for talk. I can get all
我在那客栈里就听够了
the talk I need and more at the Monarch Boarding House.
把你的钱留下
Leave your money.
明早七点来这儿找我
Meet me here tomorrow morning
然后我们出发去"猎浣熊"
at seven o'clock and we will begin our coon hunt.
最挚爱的母亲
Dearest mother,
我即将开始一段伟大的冒险
I'm about to embark on a great adventure.
我听说汤姆・切尼逃入了荒野之中
I have learned that Tom Chaney has fled into the wild.
而我将协助当局将他捉拿归案
And I shall assist the authorities in pursuit.
你知道爸爸总让我坚信正义
You know that Papa would want me to be firm in the right.
就像他一直做的那样
As he always was.
所以别为我担心
So do not fear on my account.
纵使走过死亡笼罩的幽谷
Though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death.
我也不怕遭害[圣经诗篇廿三篇四节]
I shall fear no evil.
万物的造物主俯视着我  而且
The author of all things watches over me, and
我有匹好马
I have a fine horse.
亲亲小弗兰基  捏捏维奥莱特的脸
Kiss Little Frankie for me and pinch Violet's cheek.
我父亲的死  终将迎来复仇
My Papa's death will soon be avenged.
我要出发去查克托区了
I'm off for the Choctaw Nation,
考伯恩警官呢
Where's Marshal Cogburn?
走了
Went away.
留了这个给你
Left this.
这有张回家的车票
Here inside is a train ticket for your return home.
用它回家去
Use it.
当你看到这封信时
By the time you read this,
我已经穿过河到印第安区了
I will be across the river in the Indian Nation.
你不可能追上来的
Pursuit will be futile.
我会带切尼回来的
I will return with your man, Chaney.
让我自己来完成
Leave me to my work.
鲁本・考伯恩
Reuben Cogburn.
那是考伯恩法警吗
Is that Marshal Cogburn?
对
That is the man.
他旁边是谁
Who's he with?
不知道
I do not know.
带我过去
Well, take me across.
那你就是那个逃犯
So, you're the runaway.
他告诉我  你一旦出现
Marshal told me you'd show up.
就带去见警长
I'd present you to the Sheriff.
那是瞎编的  放开我的马
That is a story. Let go my horse.
我过河有急事
I have business across the river.
如果你还是不带我过去
If you don't turn around and take me across,
那我们就法庭上见
You may find yourself in court where you don’t want to be.
我有个好律师
I have a good lawyer.
小黑  冲过去
Go, Little Blackie.
加油
Come on.
真是匹好马
That is quite a horse.
我用十美元买下它
I'll give you ten dollars for him.
用你从我这偷来的钱吗
From the money you stole from me?
那不是偷  我不已经去抓你要的人了吗
That was not stolen, I'm out for your man.
我们协商好一起走的
I was to accompany you.
如果我不去  协议便不生效
If I do not, there is no agreement
那你就是偷我的钱
and my money was stolen.
快把这孩子送回摆渡那去吧
Marshal, put this child back on the ferry.
山高路远  这简直就是浪费时间
It's a long road, and time is a-wasting.
若我现在回去
If I go back, it's to the U.S. Marshal's office
我会去警署报告  你偷了我的钱
to report the theft of my money.
考伯恩法警  "追上来也没意义"
And futile, Marshal Cogburn, "Pursuit would be futile"?
的没意义你都拼错了
It's not spelt F-U-D-E-L.
我真要打你屁股了
It's time for your spanking.
你再老三老四
Now you do as the grown-ups say!
我就拿鞭子抽烂你的腿
Or I will get myself a birch switch and stripe your leg!
法警  你就眼睁睁地看着他这么打我吗
Are you going to let him do this, Marshal.
不会  勒波义夫  放下鞭
No, I don't believe I will. Put your switch away, LeBoeuf.
不行  我开始了就不能停下
I aim to finish what I started.
那估计会是你人生中犯下的最大的错误
That'll be the biggest mistake you ever made,
你这个德州傻牛仔
you Texas brush-popper.
竟然被一小姑娘摆布
Hoorawed by a little girl.
我真不习惯生这么大的火堆
I am not accustomed to so large a fire.
在德州  我们用小树枝生小火
In Texas, we will make do with a fire of little more than twigs
或是用水牛的粪便
or buffalo chips.
用豆子来维持过夜火
Heat the nights rations of beans.
骑警队规定
And, it is Ranger
不能在生火的地方搭帐篷
policy never to make your camp in the same place as your cookfire.
在野外暴露自己的行踪  是不明智的
Very imprudent to make your presence known in unsettled country.
你怎么知道巴格比那有情报
How do you know Bagby will have intelligence?
他开了家店
He has a store.
这样就有消息来源了吗
That makes him an authority on movements in the Territory?
现在我们身在荒野里
We have entered a wild place.
不管是谁
Anyone coming in,
都需要食物的补给
wanting any kind of supply,
所以那是必经之路
cannot pick and choose his portal.
你这样做有必要吗
That is a piece of foolishness.
这季节蛇都冬眠了
All the snakes are asleep this time of year.
我有听说过冬眠起来的蛇
They've been known to wake up.
我也要根绳子
Well, let me have a rope, too.
你就不用了
A snake would not bother you.
又小又瘦的  蛇才不会喜欢
You are to little and boney.
去打点明早用的水  放在火堆旁
You should fetch the water for the morning and put it by the fire.
-小溪要结冰了  -我才不去
- The creek'll ice over tonight. - I'm not going down there again.
你想要的话  就自己去打
You want anymore water, you can go fetch it yourself.
你该庆幸  这地方这么容易打到水
You're lucky to be traveling in a place with a spring so handy.
在我那儿  连续几天都看不到一滴水
In my country you can ride for days and see no ground water.
我只能从马蹄印里弄出点脏水喝
I have lapped filthily water from a hoofprint.
这已经算幸运了
and was glad to have it.
若我遇到一个德州牛仔
If I ever meet one of you Texas waddies
说他从未喝过马蹄印里的水
who says he had never drank water out of a horse track
那我会跟他握手
I think I'll shake his hand
请他抽丹尼尔・韦伯斯特雪茄
and give him a Daniel Webster cigar.
你不相信
You do not believe it?
前二十五遍还相信
Oh, I believed it the first twenty-five times I heard it.
说不定  还真有可能是真的
Maybe, maybe this is true.
说不定舔脏水是骑警队的规定
Maybe lapping water off the ground is Ranger policy.
你太无知了  考伯恩
You're getting ready to show your ignorance now, Cogburn.
我不介意你拿我开玩笑
I don't mind a little personal chaffing.
但我不想听到
But I won't hear anything
任何拿骑警队做嘲讽对象的屁话
against the Ranger troop from a man like you.
你们骑绵羊都出名了
How long have you boys been mounted on sheep down there?
就算你的马全部倒下了
My white Appaloosa will still be galloping
我的白马依然能驰骋
when that big American stud of yours is winded and collapsed.
再敢开玩笑的话
Now make another joke about it.
你是想用你那三寸不烂之舌
You are only trying to put on a show for this girl Mattie
在小姑娘面前做表演吧
with what you must think is a keen tongue.
你说话怎么跟女人似的
This is like women talking.
是啊  没错
Yes, that is the way!
你弄得我在小姑娘眼里  显得特蠢
Make me out foolish in this girl's eyes.
我想她已经知道你是什么货色了
I think she has got you pretty well figured.
想听"午夜访客"吗
Would you two like to hear the story of "the Midnight Caller"?
其中一个扮访客
One of you is gonna have to be the caller.
我教你说什么
Now I'll tell you what to say.
我扮演其他角色
Now I'll do all the other parts myself.
-早  警官  -早
- Good morning, Marshal. - Morning.
勒波义夫先生呢
Where's Mr.  LeBoeuf?
去溪边解手去了
Down by the creek performing his necessaries.
考伯恩警长  我们正好需要私自协商下
Marshal Cogburn, I welcome the chance for a private parley.
你和勒波义夫先生之间  应该有
I gather that you and Mr. LeBoeuf have come to some,
某种协议吧
some sort of agreement.
作为你的雇主
And as your employer I believe
我有权知道  详细内容
I have the right to know the particulars.
详细内容
The particulars...
我们会把切尼交给德州执法官
...is that we bring Chaney down to the magistrate in San Saba Texas
那有丰厚的悬赏等我们去拿
where they have a considerable reward on offer, which we split.
我不想让他被带到德州
I did not want him brought to Texas,
不想让他在德州服法
to have a Texas punishment administered for a Texas crime.
这不是我们的协议
That was not our agreement.
你不是希望他被抓  然后服法吗
What you want is to have him caught and punished.
我要他为我爸服法
I want him to know he's being punished for killing my father.
那么  你可以亲口告诉他
Well, you can let him know that. You can tell him to his face.
还可以吐他口水
You can spit on him.
或者叫他吃沙  我会帮你把人按着
and make him eat sand out of the road. I can hold him down.
如果你想的话
If you want,
我会把他打得皮开肉绽
I'll flay the flesh off the soles of his feet,
然后帮你找印第安辣椒抹上去
and find you Indian pepper you can rub into the wound.
这样不值一百美金吗
Isn't that a hundred dollar value?
不值
No, it is not.
既然我付了钱  你就应该服从我
When I have brought and paid for something, I will have my way.
若不服从  为什么我要付你钱
Why do you think I'm paying you, if not to have my way.
你现在要明白
It is time for you to learn.
不是所有细节都能按照你的意愿走
You cannot have your way in every little particular.
若你不满意
If you find I fail to satisfy your terms,
等追捕结束后  我退你钱
I'll return your money at the end of this expedition.
等我和小黑回去后
Little Blackie and I are ridding back to
要把这些告诉警署  这是欺诈
the U.S. Marshal's office. This is fraud.
该死的
God damn it!
怎么了
What's going on?
我们在谈生意
This is a business conversation.
谈生意
Is that what you call it?
看起来  你还是被小姑娘摆布
Sounds to me you're still being hoorawed by a little girl.
-你说  摆布  -没错
- You say, hoorawed? - That was the word.
没有摆布  我和警官的协议
There is no hoorawing in it. In my agreement with the Marshal,
比你的早  这有法律效应的
antedates your. It has the force of law.
法律效应
The force of law?
他可是个恶名昭彰的混球
This man is a notorious thumper.
他跟着昆特里尔到处抢劫
He rode by the light of the moon with Quantrill,
还有血腥比尔・安德森
and Bloody Bill Anderson.
他们是守法公民  德州佬
Them men was patriots, Texas trash.
在堪萨斯州的劳伦斯  欺杀妇孺
They murdered women and children in Lawrence, Kansas.
简直一派胡言
That's a God damn lie!
你在哪儿服役
What army was you in, Mister?
什里夫波特市
I was at Shreveport.
先是跟着柯比・史密斯  然后
First with Kirby Smith, then with...
从属哪个部队
What side was you on?
北佛吉尼亚部队  考伯恩
I was in the army of Northern Virginia, Cogburn.
我说这个也不会掉脑袋
And I don't have to hang my head when I say it.
若你跟的是昆特里尔首长
If you had served with Captain Quantrill.
首长  昆特里尔首长
Captain! Captain Quantrill.
确实是他
That...indeed.
-不说了  勒波义夫  -哪个首长
- You had best let this go, LeBoeuf. - Captain of what?
很好
Good, then!
德州那边可没这个闲钱给我
There're not sufficient dollars in the state of Texas,
听你扯屁话
to make it worth my while to listen to your opinions.
我们之间的协议作废了
Our agreement is nullified.
正合我意
That suits me.
分道扬镳  自力更生吧
It's man for himself.
恭喜你  考伯恩
Congratulations, Cogburn.
成功从一个抢劫犯晋升为保姆了
You've graduated from marauder to wetnurse.
再见
A-dios.
我们不需要他  是吧  警官
We don't need him, do we Marshal?
会需要他的夏普斯卡宾枪吧
We'll miss his Sharps carbine.
这里可不是什么太平之地
It's apt to get lively out here.
住手
Hey!
快跑
Go on.
待在这儿  小妹妹
Stay here, sister.
我去见巴格比
And I will see Bagby.
切尼来过吗
Has Chaney been here?
没有
No.
憧伞ずＫ沽教烨袄垂
Coke Hayes was, two days ago.
憧珊凸肥涸四蔚乱换锏
Coke runs with Lucky Ned.
他用这个买了东西
He bought supplies, with this.
是爸爸的金币
Well, this is Papa's gold piece.
汤姆・切尼  等着  我们来了
Tom Chaney here we come.
这金币到处都是
It is not the world's only California gold piece.
可在这少见
They are rare here.
是很少见
They are rare.
就算是切尼的
But if it is, Chaney's,
他加入狗屎运奈德并不是唯一的可能性
Just as easily mean that Lucky Ned
他也有可能是被狗屎运奈德杀人劫财了
and his gang fell upon him, as that he fell in with them.
切尼现在可能已经是尸体了
Chaney could be a corpse.
这会令人很失望的  警官
That would be a bitter disappointment, Marshal.
那我们现在该怎么办
what would we do?
继续追捕
Um, pursue them.
不管怎么样  奈德和法警的账还没算清呢
Ned's unfinished business for the marshals anyhow.
抓到他  就等于就抓到切尼了
Or when we have him we will also have Chaney.
起码知道切尼尸体所在
or we can learn the whereabouts of his body.
巴格比不知道他们往哪儿走了
Bagby didn't know which way they went.
但起码  他们从这经过过
But now we know they come through here.
这儿只有一两条路好走
They couldn't be going but one or two ways.
一条是朝着旋梯山朝北走
Heading north, towards the Winding Stair Mountains.
另外一条就是朝西走
Pushing further west.
我猜是北边  那容易抢到东西
I suspect north. There is more to rob.
我买了家餐馆
I bought an eating place.
起名叫"绿蛙"
Called the "Green frog".
从此我自称伯勒先生
Started calling myself, Burroughs.
但我又开始酗酒了
But my drinking picked up.
妻子不喜欢我的那帮狐朋酒友
My wife did not care for the company of my river friends.
她决定重投前夫的怀抱
She decided to go back to her fist husband,
一个五金店的店员
a clerk in a hardware store.
临走前  她和我说  "再见  鲁本"
That was when she said, "Goodbye Reuben."
"你不够得体"
"A love for decency does not abide in you."
一个离婚女人竟和你谈体面
There is a divorced woman talking about decency.
我告诉她   "再见  诺拉"
I told her, "goodbye Nola."
"但愿那卖钉子的混蛋这次能令你快乐"
"I hope that little nail-selling bastard will make you happy this time."
她把我的儿子也带走了
She took my boy with her too.
反正他也不喜欢我
He never cared for me anyway.
估计是对他太凶了
I guess I did speak awful rough to him.
虽然我不是故意的
I did not mean anything by it.
谁都不想有比我儿子贺拉斯还笨的小孩吧
You would not want to see a clumsier child than Horace.
他至少打破了四十个杯子
I bet he broke forty cups...
那是切尼吗
Is it Chaney?
单从脚底  可认不出
I would not recognize the soles of his feet.
那你爬上去看看
Well, you'll have to clamber up and look.
我太老太胖了
I'm too old and too fat.
现在绿蛙那多了张桌球台
Now the Green Frog had one billiard table.
男女都能玩  不过一般都是男的在玩
Served ladies and men both, mostly men.
我曾经想自己经营
I tried to run it myself a while,
但是总是照料不好
but I couldn’t keep good help.
我一直没有学会如何买肉
And I never did learn how to buy meat.
是他吗
Is that him?
我觉得不是
I believe not.
把他放下来
Well, cut him down.
为什么
Why?
我可能认识
I might know him.
所以我就跑去了德州那火烤之地
That was when I went out to the staked plain of Texas,
和弗农・沙夫特  还有个叫奥利的
and shot buffalo with Vernon Shaftoe
平头族印第安人一起猎水牛
and a Flathead Indian named Olly.
摩门一家
The Mormons...
把沙夫特赶出了盐湖城
had run Shaftoe out of Great Salt Lake City,
别问我为什么
but don't ask me what it was for.
就当做误会好了
Call it a misunderstanding and let it go at that.
那些无赖
Well,  the big shaggies,
都散了
about all gone now.
真他妈的遗憾
Damned shame.
现在能买到腌牛舌的话  三美金我也愿意
Give three dollars right now for a pickled buffalo tongue.
为什么要把他吊这么高
Why did they hang him so high?
不知道
I don't know.
可能认为这样可以让他死得更惨
Possibly in the belief it would make him more dead.
我不认识这人
I do not know this man.
你吊死的吗
You hanged him?
为什么他把这吊死的人带走
Why is he taking the hanged man?
他认识的人吗
Did he know him?
不认识
He did not.
好歹是具尸体
But it is a dead body.
可以卖点钱
Must be worth something in the trade.
再说说我第二任妻子  埃德娜
Now my second wife, Edna.
她一直希望我成为律师
She had taken a notion she wanted me to be a lawyer.
买了本很厚的《丹尼尔协商技巧》
Bought this heavy book called Daniel's on Negotiable Instruments.
让我读
Set to make me reading it.
我从来没看懂过
Never could get a grip on it.
我很开心能够撇开它  离开德州
I was happy enough to set it aside and leave Texas.
我们离加拿大不远了
There ain’t six trees between here and Canada,
这段距离几乎寸草不生
nothing else grows but has stickers on it.
问他们...
Ask them...
-我就知道  -知道什么
- I knew it. - Knew what?
有人跟踪我们
We're being followed.
我刚嘱咐那印第安人若发现有人跟着我们
I asked that Indian to signal with a shot
就鸣枪做信号
if someone was on our trail.
我们应该担心吗  警官
Should we be concerned, Marshal?
不用  勒波义夫故意打草惊蛇
No, Mr. LeBoeuf is giving us his bird dog.
一旦计谋成功  他就会飞奔而至
He wants to cut it in, once it flushed his prey.
或许我们可以来回行走
Perhaps we could double back over our tracks,
来混淆他们的追踪
and confuse the trail in a clever way.
不用  我们就在这儿等
No, we will wait right here.
跟我们的朋友问声好
Offer our friend a warm hello.
问问他要去哪儿
Ask him where he's going.
你不是勒波义夫
You are not LeBoeuf.
我叫福斯特
My name is Forster.
我是这里的牙医
I practice dentistry in the nation.
也是兽医
Also, veterinary arts.
也开刀
And medicine,
不过是在那些不会乱动的人们身上
on those humans that will sit still for it.
看来你今天有收获啊
You have your work cut out for you there.
和一个诚恳的印第安人交易的
Traded for him with an Indian, who said he came by him honestly.
我以两面牙医镜一瓶祛痰剂作为交换
I gave up two dental mirrors and a bottle of expectorant.
你们有需要
Do either of you need
医疗救助吗
Medical attention?
没有  要开始变冷了
No. Hey! Fixing to get cold.
你知道哪儿可以避寒吗
Do you know of anywhere to take shelter?
我有熊皮保暖
I have my bearskin.
你可能想去小流氓博本那儿
You might want to head over to the Original Greaser Bob's.
他在卡里伦河那凿了个洞
He notched a dugout into a hollow along the Carrillon River.
你穿过河
If you ride the river,
就能看到了
you won't fail to see it.
小流氓博本创意旅馆
Greaser Bob's, the original.
小流氓博本
Greaser Bob...
在纠察线北边打猎
...is hunting north of the picket wire.
不会在意你借用一下的
And would not begrudge its use.
-多谢  -我已经拔了他的牙齿
- Much obliged. - Now, I have taken his teeth.
我会付价钱
I will entertain an offer,
买下他的其他部分
for the rest of him.
拿着我的大衣
Take my jacket.
轻轻地走到屋顶上
Creep onto the roof.
若他们不友好  听我指令  弄灭烟囱
If they're unfriendly I'll give you a sign to damp the chimney.
谁在外面
Who is out there?
我们想避下寒
We're looking for shelter.
没地方了  快滚
No room for you here! Ride on!
里面都有谁
Who all is in there?
滚
Ride on!
我是联邦官员
I'm a Federal officer.
里面有谁在
Who's in there?
一个圣公会教徒和一个废物
A Methodist and a son of a bitch.
我是大公鸡考伯恩
This is Rooster Cogburn.
还有哥伦布・波特和五名法警
Columbus Potter and five other Marshals is out here with me.
我们有一桶煤油
We have got a bucket of coal oil.
再过一分钟  就点燃你们的房子
In one minute we will burn your house from both ends.
你们一共就两个人
There's only two of you.
有种你就试试看
Go ahead and bet your life on it.
你们有几个人
How many of you is in there?
就我们俩
Just the two of us.
但是我的搭档中枪了
But my partner's hit.
他走不动了
And he can't walk.
你是埃米特・昆西吗
Is that Emmet Quincy?
你说房顶上的是个男的
You said it was a man on the roof.
我以为是波特呢
I thought it was Potter.
昆西  你还是一如既往的笨啊
You was always dumb, Quincy, and remain true to form.
怎么这么多玉米糊糊啊
This here's an awful lot of sofky.
你们在等同伙吗
You boys looking for company?
没有  那是我们的晚饭和早饭
No, that was supper and breakfast both.
我想早上多吃点
I like a big breakfast.
玉米糊熟了之后会变大的
Sofky always cooks up bigger than you think.
还有威士忌呢
And a good store of whiskey here as well.
你们准备这么多吃的干什么
What are you boys up to, outside of cooking banquets?
我们正在吃饭
We were just having our supper.
这种鬼天气  我们也不知道是谁在外面
We don't know who was outside in weather like this.
还以为是个疯子呢
Might have been some crazy man.
谁都可以自称是法警
Anyone could say he is a marshal.
我的腿好痛
My leg hurts.
当然痛了
I'll bet it does.
你上次见到奈德・彼伯是什么时候
When was the last time you see your old pard, Ned Pepper?
不知道  他是谁啊
I do not know that. Who is he?
你居然不记得他了
I'm surprised you don't remember him.
他是个皮包骨  又警觉又敏捷
Skinny fellow, nervous and quick,
他的嘴唇都烂了
his lip's all messed up.
还是想不起来是谁
That don't bring anybody to mind.
现在有个新来的
There's a new boy
可能在奈德手下做事
that might be running with Ned.
他脸上有个又黑又亮的弹痕
He got a powder mark on his face, black polish.
他称呼自己为切尼
Calls himself Chaney
有时也叫切尔姆斯福特
or Chelmsford sometimes.
拿一把亨利步枪
Carries a Henry rifle.
还是记不起来
That don't bring anybody to mind.
如果脸上有弹痕我应该能记住的
Black mark, I would remember that.
你什么都不记得了是吗  昆西
You don't remember nothing I want to know, do you Quincy?
你知道什么  小月
What do you know, Moon?
我们不认识你要找的那帮人
We don't know those boys you're looking for.
我不认识那帮人
I don't know those boys.
我知道一定告诉你  我坚信法理
I always try to help out the law.
等我们到史密斯堡的时候
By the time we get to Fort Smith,
你这条腿就会肿得像我的帽子一样粗了
that leg will be swelled up as tight as Dick's hat band.
这条腿就废了
It'll be mortified.
到时候不截肢都不行了
And they'll have to cut it off.
如果你活下来了
Then if you live, I'll make
我会让你在底特律的联邦监狱里
it two or three years in the federal house
-蹲个两三年  -你在威胁我
- up in Detroit, there. - You're trying to get at me.
他们会教你读书写字的  但是
They'll teach you how to read an write up there. But...
除此之外  就有你好受的了
The rest won't be so good.
那帮家伙连瘸子都会不放过的
Them boys, they can be hard on a gimp.
你在威胁我
You are trying to get at me.
现在
Now.
如果你能透露点关于奈德的消息
You give me some good information on Ned.
我明天就把你送回巴格比的商店
I'll take you down to Bagby's store tomorrow,
把你腿里的子弹取出来
get that ball taken out of your leg.
然后我会给你们三天时间离开这里
Then I'll give you three days to clear the Territory.
我们真的不认识你要找的那帮人
We don't know those boys you're looking for.
反正不是他的腿
It ain't his leg.
-我...  -你能闭嘴吗  小月
- I was... -Won't you flap your mouth, Moon?
我来说就可以了
It's best you let me do the talking.
-我要说  -我们是谨慎的捕猎者
- I would say I... - We are weary trappers.
你怎么会跟这个老恶棍在一起
Who worked you over with the ugly stick?
脸上有弹痕的那个切尼杀了我父亲
The man Chaney with the marked face, killed my father.
他也像你一样是个醉鬼
He's a whiskey drinker like you
他因为喝醉杀了我父亲
and it led to killing in the end.
好好回答法警的问题  他会帮你的
If you answer the Marshal's questions, he will help you.
我家有个很好的律师  他也会帮你的
I have a good lawyer at home, and I know he will help you too.
我有点搞不懂
I'm puzzled by these.
她为什么会在这
Why is she here?
乔  别听那个小兔崽子的鬼话
Joe, these people. Don't you go jawing with that runt.
我不喜欢你
I don't like you.
我希望你进监狱  我的律师才不会帮你
I hope you go to jail. My lawyer will not help you.
我腿疼的要昏过去了
My leg is giving me fits.
像你这样的年轻人不会想失去一条腿的
A young fellow like you don't want to loose his leg.
冷静点
Easy now.
他在引诱你
He's trying to get at you.
我从不食言
With the truth.
前天我们看到奈德和海斯了
We seen Ned and Hayes two days ago.
你脑子坏了吗  你再说我就杀了你
Don't you act the fool, if you blow I will kill you.
我受够了  我需要个医生
I'm played out, I need a doctor.
我们前天碰到奈德和Hays了
We met Ned and Hayes two days ago.
该死的
God damn it.
天啊
Oh lord.
我要死了
I'm dying.
快想想办法
Do something.
救救我
Help me.
我也无计可施了  孩子
I can do nothing for you, son.
你的伙伴要杀你  我已经替你报仇了
You pard has killed you, and I've done for him.
别让我死在这里
Don't leave me lying here.
别让狼把我吃掉的
Don't let the wolves rip me up.
我会把你安葬的
I'll see you're buried right.
跟我说说奈德  你在哪儿看到他了
You tell me about Ned, where'd you see him?
前天
Two days ago.
在巴格比的商店
Bagby's store.
他们今晚要来这里换马并拿些玉米糊
They are coming here tonight to get remounts, and sofky.
他们刚在御夫座铁路交叉处抢了飞之凯蒂
They just robbed the Katy Flyer at Wagoner's Switch.
飞之凯蒂: 最早拥有名字的火车
途径密苏里州  堪萨斯州  德克萨斯州
我要死了
I'm gone.
给我的兄弟乔治・加勒特捎个信
Send the news to my brother, George Garrett.
他在德州南部做卫理公会巡回牧师
He is a Methodist circuit rider in South Texas.
我要不要告诉他你是个逃犯
Shall I tell him you was outlawed up.
无所谓了
It don't matter.
他知道的
He knows I'm on the scout.
我会在荣耀之路上和他相见的
I will meet him later, walking the streets of Glory.
别碰见昆西
Well don't be looking for Quincy.
他们来了之后我们怎么干
What do we do when they get here?
等他们自己送上门
Well, they will ride up.
到时候我们来一个瓮中捉鳖
What we want is to get them all in the dugout.
我会干掉最后一个进去的人
I'll kill the last one that goes in,
之后他们就成瓮中之鳖了
then we will have them in a barrel.
你在他们身后放冷枪吗
You will shoot them in the back?
这样才能给他们个下马威
It will give them to know our intention is serious.
然后我会喊话
Then I will call down
看看我们能不能活捉他们
see if they'll be taken alive.
如果抓不到活的
If they won't.
他们一出来我就开枪
I'll shoot them as they come out.
干掉他们中的三个
I'm hopeful that three of their party being dead
估计他们也就没胆了
will take the starch out of them.
你看上去很沉着
You display great poise.
这跟打火鸡没什么两样
Aw,it is just a turkey shoot.
有一次在新墨西哥州
There was one time, in New Mexico,
我们被七个人追
we was being pursued by seven men.
我把马调了个头 然后用牙咬住缰绳
I turned Bo around and taken them reins in my teeth,
朝着他们直冲过去
and rode right at them boys.
拿我马鞍里的两把海军六号朝他们开火
Firing them two navy sixes I carry in my saddle.
希望他们真是如我所想的那样
Well.. I guess they was all married men who
都有老婆了  非常顾家  不能丢失性命
loved their families as they scattered and run for home.
这真的难以置信
Well that is hard to believe.
-什么难以置信  -你居然一挑七啊
- What is? - One man riding at seven.
这是真的
Well, it's true.
当你足够快足够勇猛的时候
You go for a man hard enough and fast enough,
你的对手是不会想己方有多少人的
You don't have time to think about
他只会考虑他自己
how many is with him, he thinks about himself.
考虑如何阻挡即将到来的狂风暴雨
How he may get clear of the wrath that's about to set down on you.
他们为什么要追你呢
Why were they pursuing you?
我抢劫了一个放高利贷的银行
I robbed a high-interest bank.
我总不能去抢小偷吧
Can't rob a thief, can you?
我从不抢平民的钱
Never robbed a citizen.
连一块表都没抢过
Never took a man's watch.
抢谁都不对
It is all stealing.
那帮新墨西哥州的人也这么想
That's the position they took in New Mexico.
就一个人
One man.
没想到他们会派人过来探风
I didn't figure them to send a scout.
该死的
Damn.
他是勒波义夫
It is LeBoeuf.
警官  我们必须得去提醒他
Oh, we have to warn him, Marshal.
来不及了
Too late.
我们该怎么办啊  警官
What do we do, Marshal?
静观其变  他在干什么
We sit. What does he do?
那个穿羊皮衣服的小子就是狗屎运奈德
Him in the woolly chaps, is Lucky Ned.
就是现在
Well, that's that.
计划失败
Well that didn't pan out.
你把我的计划全毁了  伙计
You managed to put a kink in my rope, partner.
我伤的很严重
Ah, I'm severely injured.
伤的不轻呢
Yes, you got rocks on.
我中枪了
I was also shot.
而且是被来复枪打中
By a rifle.
很有可能
Well that's quite possible.
我没能够按照原计划行动
The scheme did not developed as I had planned.
你肩膀中枪了  好在子弹穿过去了
You've been shot in the shoulder, but the bullet passed through.
你嘴怎么了
What happened to your mouth?
我可能咬着自己了
I believe I bit myself.
掉了几颗牙  果真啊
Couple of teeth loose, and ah yeah.
舌头都快被咬断了
Tongue bit almost through.
你想我把它留在里面还是猛的拔出来
You want to see if it'll knit or should I just yank it free.
我认识一个赶马的人
I know a teamster.
他从马背上摔下来的时候把舌头咬断了
Bit his tongue off as he was thrown from a horse.
过了很长时间才能说话
After a time he learned to make himself more or less understood.
我还是把它弄出来吧
I'll just yank it free.
现在怎么样了
What's that now.
What's that now?
会自己愈合的
Knit. It will knit.
好极了
Ah, very well.
舌头上的伤口可包扎不了
It's impossible to bind a tongue wound.
真不巧  我们刚才还碰到个医生呢
Too bad, we just ran across a doctor.
-警官  -但是我们不知道他往哪走了
- Marshal? - Of sorts, but we did not know where he was headed.
我也看到他了  所以我才过来的
I saw him too, that's how I came to be here.
这些人里没有切尼
Neither of these men are Chaney.
我知道  这几个人我都认识
I know it, I know them both.
那个长的很丑的是憧伞ずＫ
That ugly one is Coke Hayes.
这个更丑的是克莱门特・帕马利
Him uglier stiff is Clement Parmalee.
帕马利和他的兄弟们
Parmalee and his brothers
在旋梯山有一个老窝
have a silver claim in the Winding Stair Mountains.
狗屎运奈德的同伙肯定在那等他们
And I'll bet that's where Lucky Ned's gang is waiting.
我们今晚在这过夜  明早再去找他们
Well, we'll sleep here, follow in the morning.
但我们答应过他要把他安葬好的
But we promised to bury the poor soul inside.
地太硬了
Ground is too hard.
他要是想安葬的比较风光的话
That man wanted a decent burial,
他应该等到夏天再死
he should have gotten himself killed in summer.
晚安  小黑
Sleep well, Little Blackie.
我的直觉告诉我  明天就能找到他了
I have a notion that tomorrow we will reach our object.
我们紧随其后
We're hot on the trail.
我们会在旋梯山追上汤姆・切尼的
Seems that we'll overtake Tom Chaney in the Winding Stairs Mountains.
他到时候肯定不会好受
I would not want to be in his shoes.
据我了解  切尼和
As I understand it, Chaney or
切尔姆斯福特的名字是他在德州常用的
Chelmsford, as he called himself in Texas.
杀了州议员的狗
Shot the senator's dog.
当州议员要告他的时候
When the Senator remonstrated
切尔姆斯福特把他也给杀了
Chelmsford shot him as well.
你现在也许会说
Now you could argue that the shooting
枪杀那条狗是禁止的
of the dog was clearly an instance of malum prohibitum.
但枪杀议员
But the shooting of the senator
无疑是个违法的案例
is indubitably a instance of malum in se.
违什么
Malum in what?
违法的
Malum in se.
两者的区别一个是事情本身的错误
The distinction is between an act that is wrong within itself.
另外一个是违反法律规定和道德约束的
And an act that is wrong according to our laws and mores.
是拉丁语
It is Latin.
我实在吃惊
I'm struck,
你不但挨了枪子  还被人蹂躏成这个样
that LeBoeuf had been shot, trampled
舌头差点都断了
and nearly severed his tongue.
这都堵不住你的嘴
Not only does he not cease to talk,
你说话说的还挺溜
but he spills the banks of English.
有一次我离切尔姆斯福特只有两百多米
I was within three hundred yards of Chelmsford once.
可能是最近的一次了
The closest I have been.
并且在我的夏普斯卡宾枪的射程内
With a Sharps carbine that is within range.
我在马上  可以立马开枪
But I was mounted, and had the choice of firing off-hand.
也可以下马站立开枪
or dismounting and shoot from the rest.
不过这样他就和我拉开距离了
which would allow Chelmsford to augment the distance.
我还是在马上开枪了
I fired mounted.
但是打偏了
And fired wide.
如果你让枪每天都睡大觉
You could not hit a man at three hundred yards
怎么可能射中一个两百多米远的人
if your gun was resting on your Gibraltar.
夏普斯卡宾枪拥有强大的威力和精准度
A Sharps carbine is an instrument of uncanny power and precision.
我可没说枪不行
I've no doubt that the gun is sound.
我衣衫褴褛  口无遮拦
My clothes are all ragged and my language is rough.
就连我的面包也从来不服软
My bread is corn dodgers, both solid and tough
我的生活快乐又美好
And yet I'm happy, and live at my ease
就像高粱糖浆  培根和奶酪
On sorghum molasses, and bacon, and cheese
《格里尔县》  班特勒作曲
Greer county, Bantler.
我不相信他昨晚睡觉了
I do not believe he slept.
史密斯堡不远了  勒波义夫
Fort Smith is a healthy distance, LeBoeuf.
但是我想让你的马往切斯特城的方向走
But I would encourage the creature you ride to head Chester.
一只手的家伙只会拖我们后腿
Out here a one-armed man look like an easy prey.
一只眼睛枪法不准的家伙
And a one-eyed man who can't shoot.
你怎么不回去呢  考伯恩
Why don't you turn back, Cogburn?
我可得去
I'll do fine.
我知道帕马利的老窝在哪  我又没受伤
I know where the Parmalee's claim is. I'm uninjured,
我粮食充足  再说我们分道扬镳了的
well provisioned and we agree to separate.
你取消合约良心会不安的
In conscience you cannot shite our agreement.
而且是你开枪打伤了我
You're the one that shot me.
勒波义夫先生说得有道理  警官
Mr. LeBoeuf has a point, Marshal.
在竞赛中
It is unfair leg-up in any
朝对手开枪可有失公平
competition to shoot your opposite number.
他妈的  我不能接受
God damn it. I do not
你说是我开枪打了勒波义夫
accept it as a given that I did shoot LeBoeuf.
当时那么多枪都响了
There were plenty of guns going off.
我听到来福枪响了  而且感觉到了子弹
I heard the rifle, and I felt the ball.
你打偏了  考伯恩
You missed your shot, Cogburn.
我会打偏吗
Missed my shot!
你缺只眼睛可比我缺之手差多了
You are more handicapped without the eye, then I without the arm.
我能射中六十米外的蚊子眼睛
I can hit a gnat's eye at ninety yards.
那个中国佬又卖了我一堆水货子弹
That chinaman is running them cheap shells on me again.
我以为你要说  太阳刺进了你的双眼呢
I thought you were going to say, the sun was in your eyes.
对了  你只有一只眼睛
That is to say, "Your eye".
一次中两个
Two at one time.
我扔高一点
I will chuck one high.
你别开枪
Hold fire.
-中了  -中了
- There. - There?
-是我打中的  -是你吗
- My bullet. - Your bullet?
你要是能打中还会误伤我的肩膀吗
If you hit what you aim at, explain my shoulder.
先生们  在大草原上比赛射面包
Gentlemen, shooting corn bread out here on
不能帮我们找到彼伯那帮人
the prairie is getting us no closer to the Pepper gang.
再来一次  等着瞧
One more. This will prove it.
请你别开枪
Please hold fire.
这样就能找到回去的路
Find our way back.
狗屎运奈德
Lucky Ned?
Lucky Ned!
真不赖啊  考伯恩
Very good, Cogburn.
现在怎么办
Now what?
该死的
Oh, god damn it.
考伯恩才不想我吃他的粮食
Cogburn does not want me to eat out of his store.
别犯傻了
That is silly.
你一整天都没吃了  而且这些是我的
You have not eaten the whole day,and it is my store not his.
饿死他好了
Let him starve.
他既没追踪
He did not track.
也没开过枪
He did not shoot.
还好意思吃东西
Accepting food stuffs.
这都是你自找的
That was your initiative.
他一点力都没出
He did not contribute.
他是个只会挨枪子的人
He's a man, who walks in front of bullets.
我们躲在掩护后面安全地开枪的时候
Mr. LeBoeuf drew single-handed upon the Lucky Ned Pepper gang
勒波义夫在和狗屎运奈德他们单打独斗
while we fired safely from cover.
-我们  -你不应该这么说他
- We? - It is unfair to indict a man,
尤其当他的下巴都肿了
when his jaw is swollen, and tongue
舌头都快断了  他根本没法辩护
mangled and is therefore unable to rise to his defense.
我可以为我自己辩护的
I can speak for myself.
只不过对于像你这种低级醉鬼
I'm hardly obliged to answer
我才懒得和你吵架呢
the ravings of a drunkard who is beneath me.
我会到其他的地方另起炉灶的
I shall make my own camp elsewhere.
你才什么都没干呢  考伯恩
It is you who have nothing to offer, Cogburn.
你好意思吗
A sad picture indeed.
这不再是追踪犯人了
This is no longer a man hunt.
是自我堕落
It is a debauch.
德州骑警队员
The Texas Ranger
将独自去完成任务
presses on, alone.
把这个小姑娘带走
Take the girl.
我不干了
I bow out.
早知现在  何必当初
A fine thing to decide once you
在这荒芜之地撒下她不管吗
brought her in the middle of the Choctaw Nation.
我不干了  我金盆洗手了
I bow out, I wash my hands.
先生们  我们不能在这个时候闹翻啊
Gentlemen we cannot fall out in this fashion.
我们马上就要抓到汤姆・切尼了
Not so close to our goal, with Tom Chaney nearly in hand.
抓到个屁
In hand?
如果他现在没被埋在
If he is not in a shallow grave
从这去史密斯堡路上的坟堆里
somewhere between here and Fort Smith.
那就是他逃跑了
He is gone.
跑到天涯海角去了
Long gone.
这还要归功于勒波义夫先生 我们打偏了
Thanks to Mr. LeBoeuf, we missed our shot.
我们已经打草惊蛇了
We have barked and the birds have flown.
跑了  跑了  跑了
Gone, gone, gone.
狗屎运奈德的大军逃跑了
Lucky Ned's cohort gone.
你的五十美金也泡汤了
Your fifty dollars, gone.
跟我的威士忌一起泡汤了
Gone with whiskey.
这多显而易见啊
Seized in evidence.
就算他们留下踪迹也追不上了
The trail is cold if ever there was one.
我  我真是个糊涂的老头
I'm....I'm a foolish old man
被人拉进这么个徒劳无功的追捕
who'd been drawn into a wild goose chase.
居然还是被个悍妇和一个傻子拉进来的
by a harpy in trousers, and a nincompoop.
勒波义夫先生
Ah, Mr. LeBoeuf.
他爱在这儿待多久就待多久吧
He can wander the Choctaw Nation for as long as he likes.
当地的土著印第安人或许还把他当兄弟呢
Perhaps the local Indians will take him in.
他能说会道  没准能当上酋长呢
Honor his gibbering by making him Chief.
小妹妹  你爱去哪儿就去哪儿吧
You sister, may go where you like.
我们的合同终止了
Our engagement is terminated.
我不干了
I bow out.
我和你去
I'm going with you.
不行  这不可能
No, that is not possible.
我拖了你的后腿吗
Have I held you back?
我有把我会用的柯尔特龙骑兵左轮手枪
I have a Colt's Dragoon revolver, which I know how to use.
我不会给你带来负担
And I will be no more of a burden to you, as I was to the Marshal.
我担心的不是这个
That's not my worry.
你很勇敢
You've earned your spurs.
你已经证明了
That is clear now.
你已经成为一名追踪高手了
You've been an regular old hand on the trail.
但是考伯恩说的对
But Cogburn's right.
虽然我刚才没当着他的面承认
Even if I will not give him the satisfaction of consenting it.
确实追不上了
The trail is cold.
而且我也伤得不轻
And I am, considerably diminished.
你追踪切尼那么久了
How can you give up now,
怎么能说放弃就放弃呢
after the many months you've dedicated to finding Chaney?
你展示出了极大的决心
You have shown great determination.
我之前小看你了
I misjudged you.
我挑错人了
I picked the wrong man.
如果我们还有办法的话  我愿意帮你
I would go on with your company, if there were a clear way to go.
但我们只能在黑暗中摸索
But we'd be striking out blindly.
切尔姆斯福特已经逃跑了
Chelmsford's gone.
我们都追到这天荒地末了
We chased him right off the map.
这事就这样
There is nothing for it.
我回德州了
I'm bound for Texas.
你也该回家了
It's time for you to go home, too.
等警官清醒之后
The Marshal, when he sobers,
你就该回去了
is your way back.
我不回去  没找到切尼就不回去
I will not go back. Not without Chaney,
生要见人  死要见尸
dead or alive.
我也看错你了
I misjudged you as well.
来握个手吧
I extend my hand.
勒波义夫先生  求你了
Mr. LeBoeuf! Please!
再会
Adios.
我认识你
I know you.
你叫麦蒂
Your name is Mattie.
你是小麦蒂  那个记账员
You're little Mattie, the bookkeeper.
真巧啊
Isn't that something.
是的  而且我认识你  汤姆・切尼
Yes, and I know you, Tom Chaney.
你在这干什么
What are you doing out here?
来打点水
Come to fetch some water.
那你在这山里干什么
Oh, then what are you doing in these mountains, here?
虽然还没被正式任命
Well I have not been formally deputized,
但我是受命于鲁本・考伯恩警官
but I am acting as an agent for Marshal Reuben Cogburn
和帕克法官
and Judge Parker's court.
我要把你带回史密斯堡
I have come to take you back to Fort Smith.
我不去
Well I will not go.
你觉得怎么样
How do you like that?
那边有一治安团的警官会抓你去的
There is a posse of officers up there who will force you to go.
有意思
That is interesting news.
那边有多少人
And how many is up there?
五十个左右
Right around fifty.
他们都武器精良  志在必得
They're all well armed and they mean business.
现在我要你渡过小溪
What I want you to do now is come on across the creek
从我面前走到那座山上去
and walk in front of me up that hill.
我还是让那些警官来抓我吧
I think I will oblige the officers to come after me.
如果你不照着做  我就得开枪了
Well if you refuse to go, then I'll have to shoot you.
噢
Oh.
那你最好给枪上膛
Well you had better cock your piece.
一直向后扳
All the way back.
-直到锁住  -我知道怎么做
- Til it locks. - I know how to do it.
你不打算跟我走?
You will not go with me?
不  恰恰相反
Naw, it's just the other way around.
你得跟我走
You're going with me.
我要...
I will...AAAH!
我没想到你会开枪
I did not think you would do it.
-现在呢  -我有根肋骨断了
- What do you think now? - One of my short ribs is broken.
我爸爸想帮助你  你却杀了他
You killed my father when he was trying to help you.
我有一个你从他那偷的金币
I have one of the gold pieces you stole from him.
现在把另一个也给我
Now give me the other.
-我干什么都不顺  -麦蒂
- Nothing has gone right for me. - MATTIE!
我在这下面
I'm down here.
现在居然被个孩子打中了
Now I'm shot by a child.
我抓住切尼了
Chaney is taken into custody!
快救我
Help me.
麦蒂
Mattie!
警官
Marshal.
把马牵上  快走
Take them horses you got and move!
汤姆  到那山上去  别停下
Tom, get on up that hill! Don't you stop..
下面都是些什么人
Who all is down there?
考伯恩和其他五十个警官
Marshal Cogburn and fifty more officers.
再敢撒谎  我打穿你的头
Tell me another lie and I will stove your head in!
只有一个法警
Just the Marshal.
大公鸡
Rooster.
考伯恩
Cogburn!
听得见吗
You hear me?
回答我  大公鸡
You answer me, Rooster!
我要杀了这姑娘
I will kill this girl!
你知道我干得出来
You know I will do it!
她对我来说什么也不是
The girl is nothing to me!
只是个阿肯色州来的亡命者
She is a runaway from Arkansas!
非常好
That is all very well.
你建议我把她杀了吗
Do you advise that I kill her?
随你的便  奈德
Do what you think is best, Ned.
她只不过是个迷路的小孩
She's nothing to me but a lost child.
先好好想想
Think it over first.
我已经好好想过了
I have already thought it over!
这样你会过来得更快
You get mounted double fast!
如果看到你越过那座秃山  向西北去
If I see you riding over that bald ridge to the northwest,
我就放了这姑娘
I will spare the girl.
给你五分钟
You have five minutes!
马上就会有一队法警过来  奈德
There will be a party of marshals here soon, Ned!
把这姑娘和切尼交给我
Let me have the girl and Chaney
我就把他们引开六个小时
and I will mislead them for six hours!
太不够意思了  大公鸡
Too thin, Rooster!
太不够意思
Too thin!
五分钟已经快到了
Your five minutes is running!
别再说了
No more talk!
到那山上去
Get on up that hill.
安静
Quiet there!
法雷尔  看看汤姆的伤口
Farrel, see to Tom's wound.
我能来点培根吗
Can I have some of that bacon?
随便你
You help yourself.
再来点咖啡
Have some of the coffee.
我不喝咖啡  我才十四岁
I do not drink coffee, I am fourteen.
我们可没有酸奶  也没有面包
Well we do not have buttermilk, and we do not have bread.
我们补给不足
We are poorly supplied.
-她在哪儿  -你在这里干嘛
- Where she is. - What are you doing here?
我要拧断你的小细脖子
I will ring your scrawny neck.
别提这茬了
You let that go.
怎么回事
What happened, huh?
我告诉你  你就会明白我占理了
I will tell you and you will see that I'm in the right.
汤姆・切尼在史密斯堡枪杀了我爸爸
Tom Chaney there shot my father to death in Fort Smith
还抢了他两个金币
and robbed him of two gold pieces
偷了他的牝马
and stole his mare.
我听说考伯恩先生很有种
I was informed Rooster Cogburn had grit
就雇他来抓捕凶手
and I hired him out to find the murderer.
刚才我正好看到切尼在饮马
A few minutes ago I came upon Chaney watering the horses.
他不服法  我便朝他开枪了
He would not be taken in charge and I shot him.
如果我把他打死
If I had killed him
现在就不会被抓住  可我的枪哑火了
I would not be now in this fix. My revolver misfired.
是这样
They will do it.
哑火总是会让你陷入窘境
It will embarrass you every time.
姑娘们都玩娃娃  可你喜欢枪  是吗
Most girls like to play pretties, but you like guns, do ya?
我对枪一点兴趣都没有
I do not care a thing in the world about guns.
如果有的话  我就会有支好使的枪了
If I did I would have one that worked.
我中了埋伏  奈德
I was shot from ambush, Ned.
马在打响鼻  不断发出噪音
The horses was blowing and making noise.
是警官打中我的
It was that officer that got me.
你怎么还能在那大言不惭
How can you sit there and tell such a big story?
那个坑有一百英尺深  我要把你扔进去
That pit is a hundred feet deep, and I will throw you in it.
让你尖叫着腐烂
I'll leave you screaming in rot.
-现在你觉得怎么样  -你不会的
- Now how do you like that? - No you won't.
这个人不会让你为所欲为的
This man will not let you have your way.
他是你老板  你得照他说的做
He's your boss and you have to do as he tells you.
我从来都没法为所欲为
Ain't nothing going my way.
前天晚上埋伏我们的人是大公鸡吗
Was that Rooster waylaid us night before last?
是考伯恩警官和我
It was Marshal Cogburn and myself.
你和考伯恩
You and Cogburn.
真厉害
Quite the posse.
咱们走吧  奈德
Let us move, Ned.
时机到了再走  医生
In good time, Doctor.
昆西和那孩子怎么样了
What happened to Quincy and the kid?
他们都死了
They are both dead.
我当时身历其境  太可怕了
I was in the very middle of it. It was a terrible thing to see.
拜托  我们走吧  奈德
Please, let us move, Ned.
法警已经走了
The Marshal's gone.
你需要好的律师吗
Do you need a good lawyer?
我需要好的法官
I need a good judge.
憧伞ずＫ乖趺囱了
What happened to Coke Hayes,
这老家伙被从马上射下来了
the old fellow shot off his horse.
也死了
Dead as well.
这些暴行已经结束了
These depredations have come to an end.
你朋友大公鸡活捉不了几个人
Your friend Rooster does not collect many prisoners.
他不是我的朋友
He is not my friend.
他把我扔给了一群野蛮人
He has abandoned me to a congress of louts.
你从不掩饰你的想法吗
You do not varnish your opinions.
我们出发吗
Are we off?
咱们把飞之凯蒂那票赚的分了吧
Let us cut up the winnings from the Katie Flyer.
到老地方再分也来得及
They'll be time for that at the old place.
我骑那匹灰的
I will mount the grey.
你有别的任务
I have other plans for you.
我得和医生骑一匹马吗
Must I double-mount with the Doctor?
-不  -不
- No! - Nope.
逃跑的话  两人骑一匹马太冒险了
Too chancy with two men up if it comes to a race.
汤姆  你和这姑娘待在这儿
Tom, you wait here with the girl.
到老马家后我会派卡罗尔
When we reach Ma's house I will send Carroll back
带新马回来
with a fresh mount.
你天黑出发
You will be out by dark
我们在老地方见
and we'll meet you at The Old Place.
我不想这样
I do not like that.
让我和你一起走  奈德  离开这再说
Let me ride with you, Ned. Just out here anyway.
缺一匹马
I was short a horse.
这里会来大批法警的
Marshals will come swarming.
得有段时间呢  如果他们真来的话
Hours, if they come here at all.
他们会以为我们都走了
They'll think that we've all gone.
我不要一个人和汤姆・切尼在一起
I am not staying here by myself with Tom Chaney.
就这么定了
That's the way I will have it.
他会杀了我的
He will kill me.
你听见他说了  他已经杀了我爸爸
You heard him say it. He's killed my father,
现在你还要让他杀了我
and now you will let him kill me.
他不会这么干的
He will do no such thing.
汤姆  你知道柏林路口吧
Tom, you know the crossing at Cypress Forks,
圆木礼拜堂附近那个
near the log meetinghouse?
到那儿的时候  你把这姑娘留下
When you mount it, you take the girl and leave her there.
明白了吗  汤姆
You understand, Tom?
你敢动这小妹妹一根皮毛
Any harm comes to that child,
你就拿不到钱
you do not get paid.
哈罗德  让我和你骑一匹吧
Harold, let me ride up with you.
哈罗德  我从我那份里付五十块钱给你
Harold, I will pay you fifty dollars out of my winnings!
我不重的
I am not heavy.
再学个牛叫  哈罗德
Do the calf again, Harold.
事事都跟我作对
Everything is against me.
你没理由抱怨
You have no reason to whine.
你按强盗头子的话做
If you act as the bandit chief instructed,
不伤害我  就能在老地方拿到报酬
and no harm comes to me, you will get your winnings at The Old Place.
狗屎运奈德扔下我一个人
Lucky Ned has left me,
他知道我只能步行的话肯定会被抓的
knowing I am sure to be caught when I leave on foot.
得考虑怎么逃出生天了
Must think over my position and how I may improve it.
另一个加州金币在哪儿
Where's the second California gold piece?
你把爸爸的马怎么样了
What have you done with Papa's mare?
安静
Keep still.
你是在猜测老地方在哪儿吗
Are you thinking about the old place?
听着  如果你放了我
Look here, if you let me go
我就写书面证词
I will swear to an affidavit
你上法庭的时候会有利于你
and once you are brought to justice, it may go easier on you.
告诉你  我能做得更好
I tell you I can do better than that.
我不需要书面证词
I need no affidavit.
我只需要你闭嘴
All I need is your silence.
你爸和你一样爱管闲事
Your father was a busybody like you.
说实话  我不后悔杀了他
In honesty, I do not regret shooting him.
他看不起汤姆・切尼
He thought Tom Chaney was small.
嘲笑我
Humor me.
你还要给我提供书面证词
And you would give me an affidavit.
你们都和我对着干  所有人
You're all against me! Everybody....
这就是切尔姆斯福特
So that is Chelmsford.
终于离他这么近了  有点奇怪
Strange to be so close to him at last.
勒波义夫先生  你怎么会在这
Mr. LeBoeuf, how is it that you are here?
我听到枪声
I heard the shot,
到了河边
and went down to the river.
考伯恩订了个计划
Cogburn outlined a plan.
注意脚下  那有个坑
Mind your footing, there's a pit there.
计划里面他的那部分
His part,
我觉得有点鲁莽
I fear is rash.
他回来抓捕狗屎运奈德
He returns for Lucky Ned.
大公鸡
Yo, Rooster!
你会让我们过去吗
Will you give us the road?
一对四  太莽撞了
One against four. It is ill advised.
他不听劝的
He would not be dissuaded.
奈德  有几个人和那姑娘在一起
Hello, Ned. How many men are with the girl?
只有切尼
Just Chaney.
我们的协议已经执行了
Our agreement is in force.
上次我看见她时  她还好得很呢
She was in excellent health, when last I saw her.
法雷尔  我希望你和你兄弟都置身事外
Farrel, I want you and your brother to stand clear.
你也一样  医生
You as well, Doctor.
今天对你们没兴趣
I have no interest in you today.
你想干什么  大公鸡
What is your intention, Rooster?
你以为一对四能算旗鼓相当吗
Do you think one on four is a dogfall?
我要在一分钟之内要你命  奈德
I mean to kill you in one minute, Ned.
或者在帕克法官有空的时候
Or see you hanged at Fort Smith
把你吊死在史密斯堡
at Judge Parker's convenience.
你选哪种
Which will you have?
你这是独眼肥猪的
I call that, bold talk
痴心妄想
for a one-eyed fat man!
把枪拿好  你个狗娘养的
Fill your hand, you son of a bitch!
开枪啊  勒波义夫先生
Shoot them, Mr. LeBoeuf!
他们太远了  移动太快
To far, moving to fast.
大公鸡
Well, Rooster?
我被打散架了
I'm shot to pieces.
看来我们没人
Seems neither of us,
能见到帕克法官了
get's to see Judge Parker.
主啊
Oh Lord.
这一枪真绝了
Some bully shot.
至少有四百码
That was four hundred yards at least.
夏普斯卡宾枪  是...
the Sharps carbine, is a...
站起来  汤姆・切尼
Stand up, Tom Chaney.
勒波义夫先生
M...Mr. LeBoeuf!
你还活着吗
Are you alive?
勒波义夫先生
Mr. LeBoeuf!
你在那儿吗
Are you there?
我在这
I'm here.
你能爬出来吗
Can you clamber out?
不能
I cannot.
这有蛇
There are snakes!
醒着的吗
They awake?
醒着
Yes!
我被咬了
I am bit!
勒波义夫先生还活着吗
Does Mr. LeBoeuf survive?
活着呢  就算撞了下头
He does. Even a blow to the head
他也只会晕一小会
could silence him for only a few short minutes.
你哪儿被咬了
Where are you bit?
往边上看  就现在
Look away, now.
找到她了
I have her!
把我们拉上去
Up with us!
好了  勒波义夫  扶她上马
Worked it, LeBoeuf! Take her.
她被蛇咬了
Snakebit.
我们马上出发
We are off.
我会尽快找人救你
I'll send help for you as soon as I can.
别乱走
Don't wander off.
我们不能扔下他
We are not leaving him!
要是我们不找医生  你肯定活不了
I must get you to a doctor, sis, or you are not going to make it.
那枪我欠你的  伙计
I'm in your debt for that shot, pard.
永远别怀疑德州骑警
Never doubt the Texas Ranger.
走吧
Come on.
保持健康
Ever stalwart.
我们得停下
We must stop.
小黑精疲力竭了
Little Blackie is played out.
还有好几英里呢
We've miles yet.
快跑
Come on you.
不
No!
No.
这就对了  快跑
That's it, come on now.
不  停下
No, stop.
他逃跑了
He's getting away.
谁逃跑了  小妹妹
Who's getting away, sis?
切尼
Chaney.
不  不
No.. NO!
不  不  不
NO, no, no.
不
Oh, no.
不  住手
No, stop.
我真是老了
I've grown old.
四分之一世纪是一段漫长的时间
A quarter century is a long time.
到巴格比的店时
By the time we reached Bagby's store,
我的手已经黑了
my hand had turned black.
截肢的时候我还处于昏迷中
I was not awake when I lost the arm.
他们说考伯恩警官一直陪着我
The Marshal had stayed with me, I was told.
直到我脱离险境
'til I was out of danger.
但他在我醒来之前就离开了
But he departed before I came around.
一到家  我就给他发了邀请
Once home. I wrote him with an invitation,
请他下次经过耶尔县的时候过来坐坐
to come by, the next time he found himself near Yell County.
并收下我欠他的五十块钱
And collect the fifty dollars I still owed him.
我没有收到考伯恩警官的回音
I did not hear back from Marshal Cogburn.
他也没再出现
And he did not appear.
有一天我收到了警官的字条
Then one day I received a note from the Marshal,
还附了张传单
with a flyer enclosed.
科尔・扬戈与弗兰克・詹姆斯
狂野西部特别献映  每天两场
大公鸡考伯恩  他的技巧和精力将震撼你
他说他跟着狂野西部演出团巡演
He said he was traveling with the Wild West show.
老了  也胖了
Getting older and fatter.
他们到孟菲斯时  我还是想去看看他
But I like to come visit him when the show came to Memphis,
和老朋友叙叙旧
and swap stories with an old trail mate.
狂野西部演出
就算路上拖久了  他也会理解的
He would understand if the journey were too long.
他的字条虽然简短
Brief tho his note was.
却错漏百出
It was rife with misspellings.
女士您好
Yesum?
我是科尔・扬戈
I am, Cole Younger.
这是詹姆斯先生
This is Mr. James.
很遗憾告诉您  您错过了大公鸡
It grieves me to tell you that you have missed, Rooster.
他三天前去世了
He passed away three days ago.
演出团那时在阿肯色州的琼斯伯勒
When the show was at Jonesboro Arkansas.
他葬在那儿的联邦公墓里
Buried him there at a Confederate cemetery.
鲁本抱怨他晚上老睡不好
Reuben had a complaint what he referred to as night hoss?
我觉得是他承受不了暖和的天气了
And I believe the warm weather was too much for him.
我们有过难忘的日子
We had some lively times.
你和他是什么关系呢
What was the nature of your acquaintance?
我很久以前就认识警官了
I knew the Marshal long ago.
我们也有过  难忘的日子
We too had, lively times.
谢谢你  扬戈先生
Thank you, Mr. Younger.
继续坐着吧  醉鬼
Keep your seat, trash.
我把他的遗体运回故地
I had the body removed to our plot
多年来常去祭拜
and I had visited it over the years.
考伯恩  耶尔县  车站保管
毫无疑问  有很多闲话
No doubt people talked about that.
他们说  "她甚至都不认识那个人"
They say, "Well, she hardly knew the man".
"她是个神志不清的老处女吧"
"Isn't she a cranky old maid".
确实  我没结婚
It is true, I have not married.
我没有时间干这种傻事
I never had time to fool with it.
鲁本・考伯恩
我再也没有德州勒波义夫警探的消息
I heard nothing more of the Texas officer, LeBoeuf.
如果他还活着  我很愿意和他联系
If he is yet alive. I would be pleased to hear from him.
我猜他现在得有七十多岁了
I judge he would be in his seventies now.
快八十岁
And near eighty in seventy.
我希望他那乱蓬蓬的头发会整齐一点了
I expect some of the starch has gone out of that cowlick.
时间总是静静从我们身边溜走
Time just gets away from us.
是怎样的友谊  是怎样的无上快乐
What a fellowship, what a joy divine,
依靠于永恒的臂弯
Leaning on the everlasting arms.
我拥有怎样的恩惠  怎样的平静
What a blessedness, what a peace is mine,
依靠于永恒的臂弯
Leaning on the everlasting arms.
依靠  依靠
Leaning, leaning,
安全  安心  免于惊扰
safe and secure from all alarms.
依靠  依靠
Leaning, leaning,
依靠于永恒的臂弯
leaning on the everlasting arms.
这条朝圣之路多么甜蜜
Oh, how sweet to walk in this pilgrim way,
依靠于永恒的臂弯
Leaning on the everlasting arms
这条路日复一日  愈发光明
Oh, how bright the path grows from day to day,
依靠于永恒的臂弯
Leaning on the everlasting arms.
依靠  依靠
Leaning, leaning,
安全  安心  免于惊扰
safe and secure from all alarms.
依靠  依靠
Leaning, leaning,
我依靠于永恒的臂弯
I'm leaning on the everlasting arms.